<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl"><body><div><pb facs="#f146"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To dye a red color one needs to take a large handful
<lb/>of fine linen and then one takes a half pound of safflower, where those
<lb/>safflowers need to be bundled in a little linen bag and then one puts
<lb/>the safflower that are in the little bag in rainwater for six or seven hours
<lb/>to soak, and now and then turn the little bag in the water.
<lb/>And when it has soaked long enough one needs to wash the little bag,
<lb/>without it coming open, as long as the little bag is still red [OR: long enough until the little bag becomes red]
<lb/>Now, to make the lye, you must take grapevine wood
<lb/>and burn it to ashes, of which ashes one needs to take
<lb/>a pot full and one puts them in a kettle with two pots
<lb/>of rainwater. And leave it thus only a half hour to cook, and then take
<lb/>the kettle off the fire and let it settle, as the lye must
<lb/>be clear. And then begin to dye, end then place the little bag
<lb/>with the safflower in a dish and shake over it a clean
<lb/>little beer glass half full of lye, shake it over the little bag and 
<lb/>wash the little bag with it and then wring the little bag
<lb/>half out, and then add in the whitest linen and once it is wet
<lb/>then squeeze it out, then take a little dish of vinegar and put that little piece
<lb/>of linen in the vinegar, about a little glassfull, then squeeze it out, take again the
<lb/>same little piece of linen that had been in the dye, put it again
<lb/>in the same dye, squeeze it out thus, and put it again in the
<lb/>same vinegar, then squeeze it out. Then, throw the vinegar out and put
<lb/>clean vinegar in the little dish, and then throw the dye out also
<lb/>Wring the aforesaid little bag out, then take the previous
<lb/>piece that is still dyed and put it again therein, so then squeeze it
<lb/>out again and place it again in the vinegar, then squeeze it out again. Then
<lb/>the piece is red enough. Then, you must take once more another white piece
<lb/>of linen, and place it in the dye and then again in the vinegar just as
<lb/>before; and once the dye becomes clear, then throw it out and then lay the
<lb/>little bag in the dish, then pour another half little glass of lye over the
<lb/>little bag, and then wring it therewith, wring the little bag half
<lb/>out, and then begin to dye again in the same manner as before.
<lb/>And as you notice that there is no more dye coming out and [it runs] clear,
<lb/>then you must stop dyeing, then you must wash the red linen, 
<lb/>with some Spanish [i.e., castille] soap, but you must put the soap in a clean
<lb/>little cloth and then beat the little cloth with the soap there in the water. Thus
<lb/>must you then wash [it], piece by piece, in a bucket, and then rinse with clean
<lb/>water. Then wring it out and lay it in a dish and then put 
<lb/>vinegar over it. Let it stand thus therein for a whole night. Then the next day,
<lb/>wring it out, and then lay it to dry on a serge, and that
<lb/>in the dark, and then once it is dry, you must stiffen it with white starch.
<lb/>You must take a quarter of a pound and then let it become cold.
<lb/>Then must you thus stiffen linen, and out of one another, put [it] also on a
<lb/>serge, and that in the dark. Let it dry thus.
<lb/>Now, to make white roses, so must you take white linen and put
<lb/>it in the soap water that the red linen was washed in,
<lb/>and with clear water rinsed, but put it in no vinegar, though
<lb/>stiffen it as before.
</ab>

</div></body></text>