<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl">
<body><div>
    <pb facs="#f002"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Way for melting silk gum, or other-
<lb/>wise said tragacanth gum;
<lb/>One takes for this one patar of the said gum; it
<lb/>is necessary to put it to soak, in a half pint
<lb/>of rainwater, better more than less. One needs to
<lb/>leave it like that for two days, then one needs to take
<lb/>a spoon and stir it well, and hit it with it
<lb/>until such time it becomes a clear glue-pap, and if
<lb/>one sees that the soup is too thick, one needs
<lb/>to pour in a bit of water, until such time that it
<lb/>is good; then one needs to make it boil, a
<lb/>bit, and that while stirring it still. After that,
<lb/>one needs to pass it through a cloth, and after that,
<lb/>use it to starch silk with it.
<lb/>Way to make silk flowers
<lb/>Note: when the silk is very well peniez, put it on top
<lb/>of glass, very flat, the size of one window pane,
<lb/>reasonably big enough. Next, one needs to take the flat side of a knife,
<lb/>and take the silk gum with it. Next, one needs to spread it on top
<lb/>of the silk with it, and that also for a long time, that the silk becomes very well
<lb/>moistened, and fatty. After that, one needs to turn it over, and
<lb/>one needs to do the same. After that, one needs to put it on top of a
<lb/>towel, to let it dry in the wind, and or otherwise also.
<lb/>Next one needs to apply it, and put it on top of the form; and 
<lb/>go over it with a pierre liquoire. And dry it near to
<lb/>the fire, and or else above a stove. Next, remove it
<lb/>from there. And then cut flowers from it, of all kinds
<lb/>that you want to make. But one needs always to keep
<lb/>silk prepared for making flowers between white paper.
<lb/>The same also for silk that is not yet prepared for making flowers.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f003"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Way to undye cambric dyed with gamboge
<lb/>One needs to tie up the
<lb/>piece of cambric [to a rod?] quasi all as large as
<lb/>the piece and, next to wet it a bit,
<lb/>and rub it between the hands, well enough, then
<lb/>one needs to plunge it and wash it in hot water,
<lb/>or else in lye, like one
<lb/>washes white cambric, changing the water
<lb/>from time to time, until such that the
<lb/>cambric becomes perfectly white. One needs to tie up
<lb/>the piece of cambric two or three times for
<lb/>this end.
<lb/>Cambric, dyed with saffron and
<lb/>gamboge, is undyed in the same manner also
<lb/>The way to undye crimson or incarlacque fabric
<lb/>One needs to take two pints of lye, made from vine
<lb/>ashes, with a half pint of rainwater or fountain water.
<lb/>One must boil that together with some small pieces of
<lb/>crimson fabric, which you all let boil until such that the
<lb/>dye becomes boiled out of the fabric and it becomes all undyed. Next one
<lb/>needs to take it out of the earthenware pot, which you keep for this use, and
<lb/>after having pressed the lye out, one + needs to take yet an other piece
<lb/>of incarlacque and make it boil in the same manner. But
<lb/>each time that you press the lye out, one needs always to re-cast
<lb/>it into the pot. One needs to continue like that all until such that you
<lb/>see that the incarlacque does not undye further and that it remains beautiful. A dont
<lb/>is the dye good, a dont one needs to take the gum that you have 
<lb/>soaked and melted for a space of 24 hours. In stirring from time
<lb/>to time, being still rather thick, one needs to pass it through a very white
<lb/>cloth. Next one needs to throw the gum in the said dye and let it
<lb/>boil all together until such time that the soup becomes very thick, a
<lb/>dont you can use it to draw with a paintbrush. ✠
</ab>

<pb facs="#f004"/>
<ab>
<lb/>read at this ✠ But when the dye
<lb/>is too fatty, or too thick, and or too
<lb/>dry, one needs always to amortirre [quench/temper?] and
<lb/>stretch it out with rainwater or fountain water. And that
<lb/>until such that you see that the dye is good
</ab>

<pb facs="#f005"/>
<ab>
<lb/>for you to use with the paintbrush, to
<lb/>draw with, on cambric, and on paper.
<lb/>All the little pieces of crimson fabric, which the
<lb/>tailors throw aside, they are good for that. It is not
<lb/>necessary to have large pieces.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f006"/>
<ab>
<lb/>How one needs to accommodate cloths to make flowers
<lb/>After cambrics, muslins, and 
<lb/>cloths are very well washed and well dried,
<lb/>one needs to take, or make, a nice starch
<lb/>fairly thick, and then starch your canvases or
<lb/>cambrics in the same manner, just as one
<lb/>starches coiffures. Then one needs to hang the
<lb/>cloth by cords. Being well dry, one needs
<lb/>to pass the hand over it, on both sides of the cloth,
<lb/>to render it very uniform, then fold them by
<lb/>hand; from there, put them in a paper. One
<lb/>needs to keep oneself from using the
<lb/>iron, as one [commonly] passes over cloths, nor other
<lb/>instruments for this end. One needs to observe
<lb/>this command for all other colors too.
<lb/>This sort of canvas can only serve
<lb/>for completely white flowers without being
<lb/>drawn upon.
<lb/>Another white cambric, to be able to be 
<lb/>drawn upon
<lb/>One needs to take starch white,
<lb/>as much as can fit in a small spoon, better more than less, with
<lb/>as much as can be of starch blue, as much as
<lb/>you would like to have blue. Then one needs to take
</ab>

<pb facs="#f007"/>
<ab>
<lb/>half a glass of fish glue, then
<lb/>mix well and break the starch white into the glue. Next one
<lb/>needs to put the starch brown-blue in it, and mix it well. Then plunge
<lb/>the cambric immediately into the soup, until the soup becomes completely penetrated
<lb/>into the cambric but very well wet. One needs to open it well, and press, and
<lb/>turn it over, and rub it a bit, many times, so that the white becomes well
<lb/>penetrated into the cambric. From there, attach it to a cord with pins.~~
<lb/>but if the cord is made of horse hair, it is enough to
<lb/>hang it, taking care that the end from which it hangs
<lb/>does not attach itself together. This command must be
<lb/>observed for all other colors.
<lb/>To make yellowish cloths for 
<lb/>jasmine and other flowers, one needs to put
<lb/>with this starch white and fish glue
<lb/>three or four drops of gamboge
<lb/>To make some reddish ones
<lb/>One needs
<lb/>to take starch white, fish glue,
<lb/>and three or four drops of carmine. This
<lb/>kind of cambric is used to make carnations
<lb/>and other flowers
<lb/>Cloths of this sort can be green
<lb/>One makes them
<lb/>as above, by pouring a few drops from
<lb/>the bottle in which there is green. And if
<lb/>you want to have yellowish color, you put throughout
<lb/>the glue and the green one drop or two of
<lb/>gamboge.
<lb/>Blue cambric is made with starch brown-blue
</ab>

<pb facs="#f008"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Yet another kind of pale blue
<lb/>for the beginning of blue alimon and
<lb/>blue ranunculus, much better than
<lb/>starch pale-blue; ~
<lb/>One needs to take a piece [of]
<lb/>new blue cloth, which one calls the
<lb/>dye of Bruges, very clean. One needs to put
<lb/>it to soak for a bit in cold water. Next one
<lb/>needs to wash [until?] only the red or black soup
<lb/>removes itself. One needs to throw this water away,
<lb/>then one needs to take another clear water,
<lb/>cold also. Next one needs to wash it once 
<lb/>more in this water. Being well washed and
<lb/>the water being very blue, one needs to take it out of
<lb/>the water and wring it out well. Next, one needs to leave this
</ab>

<pb facs="#f009"/>
<ab>
<lb/>water there like that, without stirring it, for three or
<lb/>four hours, more or less. Next, one needs
<lb/>to throw  the clear water away and keep the bottom.
<lb/>Then one needs to take your cloth and cambric
<lb/>and plunge it into a small part of this water
<lb/>so well that you shouldn’t press the water out. After
<lb/>that, one needs to hang it from a cord. Being dry,
<lb/>one needs to do the same thing again until
<lb/>the moment that you see that the color is
<lb/>as you want to have it. Being dry,
<lb/>one needs to starch it in hide glue
<lb/>without pressing it out. This is why one needs
<lb/>to take only a small amount of the said glue
<lb/>so that the cambric becomes very well wetted
<lb/>without dripping once being hung by a cord.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f010"/>
<ab>
<lb/>and fish glue. One
<lb/>needs to cut the cambric in the length of
<lb/>two or three quarters and the width of three tailes [full sizes?]
<lb/>or a half square. Each piece of cambric
<lb/>or muslin must be washed piece by
<lb/>piece in the glue without taking more glue
<lb/>than that needed for the piece to be completely wet with the
<lb/>blue too. Then rub the blue very gently into
<lb/>the cambric, and when it is very blue, one needs to hold
<lb/>each one by the end in the hand and next pass
<lb/>the hand over it, from one end to the other, then back
<lb/>again, and so forth to make it 
<lb/>very even. Next, you attach it or hang it 
<lb/>by cord. But if the cambric is dry and
<lb/>it is not blue enough, one needs to plunge it again
<lb/>once more in the same soup, and do as
<lb/>above but without using starch white. These
<lb/>cambrics and[=are?] for making alimon, which one
<lb/>calls archbishops, as also for hyacinths and
<lb/>bleuels, &amp;c. ~~~ hide glue is
<lb/>		also good for making that
<lb/>		and is even better than the other
<lb/>Pale blue is made in the same way
<lb/>but instead of taking starch brown-blue
<lb/>one needs to take starch pale-blue. ~
<lb/>This muslin is used for the beginning
<lb/>of archbishops; note that pale blue is made with
<lb/>		starch brown-blue
<lb/>		[and] is the most beautiful of all the other
<lb/>		colors
<lb/>Note: archbishops are blue or violet alimon;
</ab>

<pb facs="#f011"/>
<ab>
<lb/>The brown-blue and pale blue for
<lb/>archbishops, once cut, one needs to trace
<lb/>them with carmine.
<lb/>Another blue that one uses for
<lb/>the underside of archbishops, which one sees
<lb/>hardly at all because the colors are not worth anything
<lb/>even though they are beautiful in appearance. 
<lb/>One needs to take a square or two of lacmus
<lb/>that one pounds, well bound in a good
<lb/>cloth, then put it to soak for one day and one
<lb/>night. Next, you boil it with a
<lb/>pint and a half of rainwater, better too little than
<lb/>too much. Pressing the cloth with a stick
<lb/>where it is blue, and inside, so that all of the blue
<lb/>leaves it. Then one needs to put the cambric or
<lb/>the cloths in the soup to boil together.
<lb/>Being boiled a little, one needs to take it
<lb/>out of the soup and hang it over cords.
<lb/>Being dry, if they are plainly not blue
<lb/>enough, one can plunge them again
<lb/>in the same soup, and that several times
<lb/>if there is need. Being dry, one
<lb/>puts them in fish glue or hide glue.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f012"/>
<ab>
<lb/>For making more pansy; for making alimon,
<lb/>and ranunculus; one needs to take, three mussel shells
<lb/>full of mien rouge [my red? Same red?], one needs to rub it well
<lb/>with a piece of marble, on top of some marble or some gres [sandstone?];
<lb/>being well rubbed; one needs to throw it in a glass, or the 
<lb/>third part of a glass, of the hide glue, with a 
<lb/>mussel shell full of vermillion, one needs to 
<lb/>stir it well, and to mix it together; next on needs to throw
<lb/>the white cambric into the glue, and turn it well, and
<lb/>press it well, and return it in the hands, rubbing it a 
<lb/>little, in order that the dye will be well penetrated, and that
<lb/>the cambric, muslin; and toile will be a good red;
<lb/>after that, one needs to squeeze the glue, and dye
<lb/>within, so well that it stays reasonably well wetted,
<lb/>then one needs to hang in the attic; and being dry,
<lb/>the toile, cambric, and muslin; being cut into
<lb/>leaves, one needs to put a clear carmine on it; that 
<lb/>you see to be a very beautiful color to your liking;
</ab>

<pb facs="#f013"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note if you see that the dye is too thick
<lb/>with a glass of hide glue; one needs to take
<lb/>more still, all until such time that the soup is good ◆
<lb/>Note when you would like to make less a dont [which?] one needs to 
<lb/>take some vermillion, and some mien [mine?] to your liking,
<lb/>and mix them well in hide glue; next take all at 
<lb/>once that which you have prepared for dyeing; and throw it right away 
<lb/>into the glue, or otherwise said in the soup; one needs to rub it very little,
<lb/>but instead of this, one needs to press it very well, and 
<lb/>put it back, and open it up; and after that press it again, and put it back,
<lb/>all until such time that the dye is well penetrated in 
<lb/>the cambric; in the end, if you see that you have too much
<lb/>soup, or that the cambric is too wetted, one needs to put
<lb/>still more pieces of cambric inside, so well that you 
<lb/>should not have to press anything out; one still needs to press it all 
<lb/>together; so that it penetrates in the dye also;
<lb/>But if you see to the contrary, that you do not have 
<lb/>enough glue and dye for the quantity that you have
<lb/>started to dye; a dons [then?], one needs to take all of the fabric out,
<lb/>next pour the glue, in the saucer; and one needs to mix 
<lb/>in still more dye, after that throw it the mass inside;
<lb/>and do as here before; but the glue, and the cambric, must be hot
</ab>

<pb facs="#f014"/>
<ab>
<lb/>The blue for flowers, which one calls
<lb/>areniez, is made with English ash, 
<lb/>in the same manner as the starch blue, 
<lb/>but the blue of English ash does not 
<lb/>have to be rubbed into the toile as strongly as the 
<lb/>starch blue, because the color is finer
<lb/>and it suffices, that the cambric has the color of 
<lb/>this blue, ~~~
<lb/>For making red ones one needs to take
<lb/>some vermillion, and hide glue,;
<lb/>the toiles being cut, in leaves, one needs to put a 
<lb/>clear carmine on top,: fish glue is
<lb/>also good, but with hide glue, the carmine
<lb/>is easier to trace, one needs to rub the cambric
<lb/>in the said soup, as you did
<lb/>with the English ash, this toile is useful 
<lb/>for making ranunculus, allimone, and Constantinople tulip ~~~
<lb/>The green toiles are made with hide glue,
<lb/>and some green from the bottle, without white
<lb/>starch; fish glue is also good,
<lb/>but dried cambric, one needs to plunge it 
<lb/>again into this glue because
<lb/>the green thins it too much, but hide glue
</ab>

<pb facs="#f015"/>
<ab>
<lb/>it is sufficient with the first time, and if 
<lb/>you would like to have it yellowish, one needs to put
<lb/>amongst the glue, and the green a few drops of
<lb/>gamboge, these kinds of muslin,
<lb/>etc are useful for the beginnings of ranunculi, and
<lb/>allimon? &amp;.c ~~~
<lb/>To dye jonquil color, one
<lb/>needs to take the size of a big nut
<lb/>of gamboge, with a little whole saffron,
<lb/>without being pounded, which one needs to
<lb/>put to soak in a little water, it 
<lb/>is enough that the water in the little pot ~
<lb/>will be around height of the gamboge; and the saffron in
<lb/>another little pot; leave it to extract its colour well,
<lb/>with a little hot water; the 
<lb/>gamboge being melted, one needs to 
<lb/>pour out half, into the fish glue,
<lb/>the quantity of half a glass,
<lb/>approximately, then one needs to take a 
<lb/>little of this saffron soup, that you
<lb/>stir all together, in the glue, next,
<lb/>one needs to take the cambric, and ~
<lb/>wash one piece, in the said soup, to see 
<lb/>if the color is to your agreement,
<lb/>but if it is too high yellow, one needs
</ab>

<pb facs="#f016"/>
<ab>
<lb/>to put there into the gamboge, in the same
<lb/>soup, until it is good, and ~ 
<lb/>when the color is too pale yellow; one needs to 
<lb/>put more saffron soup there, and to make
<lb/>as I said above, as also with a little bit of 
<lb/>glue, For an escalin of gamboge, with
<lb/>for six liards of saffron, makes a beautiful 
<lb/>color, one needs to put also for two liards alum
<lb/>ground, and that well done, break up, and stir together, with water; ~
<lb/>&gt;For light yellow, one only needs to take 
<lb/>the gamboge, with fish
<lb/>glue; but if the yellow is for tracing, one
<lb/>needs to take some hide glue; because
<lb/>the carmine traces more easily 
<lb/>on cambric, with this sort of glue.
<lb/>Note, that gamboge, and saffron soup is beautiful together
<lb/>without alum also the same for gamboge +alone without alum inside, it is purer; 
<lb/>Note, all yellow colors, and yellowish,
<lb/>as also red colors of vermillion,
<lb/>when it is for tracing, one needs to always starch
<lb/>with hide glue, ~ ~ ~
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>✹Carmine is mixed with a little rain,
<lb/>or fountain, water, then one needs to leave it
<lb/>to soak for one day, and one night, before
<lb/>using it to trace; carmine must be 
<lb/>broken up, or separated, in an oyster shell, or 
<lb/>else in a glass, very flat, with the amount of a
</ab>

<pb facs="#f017"/>
<ab>
<lb/>little spoon, better more than less, ~
<lb/>but when this water is almost all traced,
<lb/>one needs to pour into it several drops
<lb/>of water, and continue thus until such time that
<lb/>the carmine is all traced, each time
<lb/>that you plunge your paintbrush, in the carmine,
<lb/>one does not need to plunge it too far in, ~
<lb/>in order to not strongly move ~ the bottom;
<lb/>by ~ thus the carmine; will be more profitable for you. ~~~~
<lb/>For tracing violet, one needs to mix in 
<lb/>a little pot, or in an oyster shell,
<lb/>or else, in a flat glass, some English
<lb/>ashes, with four, or five, drops of clear
<lb/>gum, the blue being well mixed with the 
<lb/>gum, one needs to pour into it, in order to brighten the
<lb/>soup six, or eight drops of rain, or fountain,
<lb/>water, then one needs to let it soak 
<lb/>together, three, or four hours, then,
<lb/>you can trace your cambric, and likewise
<lb/>paper, as one paints the flowers,
<lb/>one needs to plunge the paintbrush in the dye
<lb/>stirring the bottom a little, in order that
<lb/>the blue, gives its dye; but when the 
<lb/>soup is almost all traced, and that in the
</ab>

<pb facs="#f018"/>
<ab>
<lb/>bottom the dye is not yet all ~
<lb/>used, one needs to put in it a few drops of water,
<lb/>with one drop of gum ~; but not
<lb/>each time that you put in water; but
<lb/>only when you see that the blue
<lb/>is not tracing well, for when this blue has too much
<lb/>gum it is in danger of shining, and it 
<lb/>spoils the harmony of blue; after the blue
<lb/>is traced, and very dry; on the traced
<lb/>cambric; one needs to trace there on top of the said blue a 
<lb/>light carmine. ~~~ for pinks,
<lb/>For dyeing pink color; one needs to
<lb/>take a quarter of safflower, which one
<lb/>puts in a little bag, of white cloth; 
<lb/>then one puts it to soak in a bucket 
<lb/>of rain, or fountain, water; immediately one
<lb/>washes the safflower a little, by changing its
<lb/>water two times, then leaves it to soak,
<lb/>from five thirty, at night, until
<lb/>five thirty, in the morning; one needs to
<lb/>take great care; that the little bag is good 
<lb/>and well tied; in order that the safflower does not leave it;
<lb/>next one needs to wash it, by
<lb/>changing the water; from time to time, and that without
</ab>

<pb facs="#f021"/>
<ab>
<lb/>wringing the little bag, but only pressing it,
<lb/>a little, with the hand, the water out from it; and when
<lb/>the water remains clear, it's a sign that the
<lb/>safflower is washed enough; the last time
<lb/>that you remove water from it, one needs to ~
<lb/>press it well, and wring the little bag in order that
<lb/>the water leaves from there entirely. but + + if you want one needs to
<lb/>keep the last rinse without moving it, all until the time that
<lb/>you have need of the first rinse for the pink color for which one
<lb/>needs to pour the clear water out, without moving the bottom, [the quantity] of a pint  +  + and more still and you throw
<lb/>this in the first rinse ~~
<lb/>Next one pulls it from the sack, and puts it
<lb/>in a large terrine, very clean; one needs to clear it well [from the little sac] in putting it ~
<lb/>in the terrine, then one breaks it up with the
<lb/>hand above, a little rain or fountain 
<lb/>water; next one pours right
<lb/>before the safflower, and this very gently, a 
<lb/>pint of lye; which one makes with ~
<lb/>ashes, which are made with vine wood;
<lb/>next cover it well, with a terrine of 
<lb/>the same size, [or] with some cover,
<lb/>in order that air does not enter there at all, leave it ~
<lb/>two hours like this; next one
<lb/>kneads it like one does bread, for the space
<lb/>of a quarter of an hour, then one needs to put it again in
<lb/>the little sac, to move it, into a
</ab>

<pb facs="#f022"/>
<ab>
<lb/>✠
<lb/>Note, before pouring the safflower into 
<lb/>the little sack, in order to wring it more easily,
<lb/>one needs to take in one hand a
<lb/>handful of safflower; and press it like that
<lb/>in the soup; next, being very well pressed,
<lb/>all of the soup [being] outside, one needs to continue like
<lb/>that, all until the time, that all of the safflower is
<lb/>pressed; next one needs to pour it immediately into 
<lb/>into the little sack, and press well all of
<lb/>the soup outside; next you make use of it immediately;
<lb/>Note, if you have a little too much lye, a
<lb/>pint and a half, more or less, according to the quantity
<lb/>of safflower; you can pour on the safflower
</ab>

<pb facs="#f023"/>
<ab>
<lb/>the soup that has been pressed outside of it, and 
<lb/>that into an earthenware pot also; next
<lb/>one needs to do with [this], as you have
<lb/>done at first; that sometimes gives
<lb/>color; after you have washed
<lb/>the cambric in this soup; one needs to 
<lb/>throw it, in the soup of the first color;
<lb/>but only, when all the
<lb/>first colors have been removed; likewise
<lb/>also, all of the rinse : ~~
<lb/>so well, that this color there, does
<lb/>not need to be rinsed until after all the
<lb/>other pink colors, also;~
<lb/>one needs to wash it well, in the rinse;~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f024"/>
<ab>
<lb/>___ il faut le partager entre fois, sans repeter, ou trois, entre et __,
<lb/>cela  __afin de tans mi sur prises ________
<lb/>very clean terrine, one needs to wring the
<lb/>sack, as hard as one can, in order that
<lb/>all of the soup leaves it. ~~~ ✠
<lb/>Next, one prepares, right away another
<lb/>terrine, with a pint of white wine vinegar,
<lb/>very clear, one plunges the cambric,
<lb/>piece by piece, in the said vinegar, until
<lb/>such time, that it is very wet, on needs to take
<lb/>the weight, of a quarter [of a pound], less, a 
<lb/>half ounce of cambric; all being ~
<lb/>very wet, one needs to take them immediately
<lb/>in the hand, in good order, without ~
<lb/>leaving a single piece behind; one needs to hurry when
<lb/>one does this, and the cambric must be ready
<lb/>in the vinegar, at the same time, as
<lb/>the soup has passed all through the little sack,
<lb/>but the person who had kneaded, and passed the
<lb/>safflower, needs to take care not to wet
<lb/>their hands in the vinegar, before the
<lb/>person who had wetted the cambric in the
<lb/>vinegar, he gives to him the mass, between the hands,
<lb/>Having received it, she plunges it immediately, all
<lb/>~ the cambric at the same time in the said soup;
<lb/>one needs to wash it well, and clear it, and
</ab>

<pb facs="#f025"/>
<ab>
<lb/>that with a light hand, as quickly as one
<lb/>can, until such time as the cambric is very
<lb/>red, and well penetrated in the dye, then
<lb/>one washes it piece, by piece, a little, and one ~
<lb/>presses it with the hand, as hard as one can, ~
<lb/>then one throws it in the verjus piece, by piece, one needs to 
<lb/>work it well, and plunge, then one needs to press the verjus outside. ~~
<lb/>Next one throws them in a terrine, prepared 
<lb/>with three pints of water, to rinse them, one piece
<lb/>at a time, one needs to work it well, but without
<lb/>rubbing, in any way, from there one takes it from
<lb/>this water, one needs to + a little press + the water outside, and one throws it
<lb/>in four, or three, other terrines in succession,
<lb/>prepared with two pints of water, in each
<lb/>terrine, ✠ when one is at the final water, one
<lb/>needs to press the water very hard out of the cambric, ~
<lb/> next one puts it, and plunges in a half
<lb/>pint of verjus, more, or less, hauling it up
<lb/>so that one can see, the quantity of cambric, in
<lb/>pulling the cambric, piece, by piece, out of the verjus
<lb/>~ one presses it in the hand, not quite as strongly
<lb/>~ as before, next on puts it in a
<lb/>very clean terrine, and very dry, waiting
<lb/>for all the other pale colors to be
<lb/>dyed, to hang them, all together in
<lb/>the attic, with the windows closed, likewise all the other
<lb/>yellowish colors, etc.,
<lb/>This done, one washes again one piece ~
<lb/>of cambric, in the soup wetting it ~
<lb/>in the vinegar also, if there is any left, 
<lb/>✠but without pressing the water outside, except at the 
<lb/>last rinse;~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f026"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note a half pint of verjus, more or less; ∞&amp;
<lb/>in hauling it up, so that one sees the quantity of cambric, is ~
<lb/>enough to plunge the cambric of the pink color;∞
<lb/>and if you have the soup of a lemon, or two, you∞
<lb/>can press the soup all out of it, into the verjus~
<lb/>also; ( but one needs to take care to never soak the 
<lb/>cambric in verjus after it is rinsed, for reason
<lb/>that this spoils the colors in little time; ( I believe =
</ab>

<pb facs="#f027"/>
<ab>
<lb/>that you understand well; when you make ∞
<lb/>a half pound of safflower; that you need ~
<lb/>to take two pints of lye, made with 
<lb/>vine ashes; and for three quarters [of a pound], three ∞
<lb/>pints; and for a pound, four pints, ◆
<lb/>note, when you do not have do not have any lemons; it is not
<lb/>necessary for you to use them, in any way; ~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f028"/>
<ab>
<lb/>for otherwise it is not necessary to put it
<lb/>in the vinegar, because the soup, is sour from the
<lb/>first cambric, then one washes again another 
<lb/>piece, if one sees that the soup is giving color
<lb/>still, then one does, as here before, this cambric
<lb/>must be kept from the elements, because the color
<lb/>is not so pure as the first, and it sticks
<lb/>to itself, ~~~  Note; when one wants
<lb/>to have very red cambrics, one needs to rinse them, only
<lb/>in three terrines of water ◆
<lb/>Note, one pound of safflower, for one 
<lb/>pound of cambric makes a beautiful color; but
<lb/>one ounce, or an ounce and a half less, makes a
<lb/>more beautiful color; and when one wants to have
<lb/>several red brown colors; one needs to divide
<lb/>the soup, in three parts; and take
<lb/>some cambric as you wish, one time
<lb/>a little more, and the other time a little 
<lb/>less; and hauling it up such that you see that the
<lb/>color is as one wants to have it, ~~~
<lb/> that which follows is to make, several pale colors
<lb/>for pinks &amp;c. ~~ 
<lb/>After the first cambric is rinsed,
<lb/>one takes, two, or three pieces of cambric, or of ~
<lb/>muslin, all dry, and very white,
<lb/>without putting it in the vinegar; and one washes it
<lb/>all immediately in :+: :+:: the verjus, then one presses it outside, and one throws it in:+: the first rinse, one 
<lb/>washes it also + + a long time, that it becomes red, next one
<lb/>washes it strongly also, in the three other rinses, in
</ab>

<pb facs="#f029"/>
<ab>
<lb/>succession, to the last, one needs to 
<lb/>press the water outside well, from there one puts it in
<lb/>the verjus; next one takes again 
<lb/>another piece, and one does as the first,
<lb/>and one continues it [with] the other pieces of cambric ~
<lb/>Like that, until the time that the rinse, 
<lb/>gives no more colors, as appropriate and ~
<lb/>when one removes the cambric out of the verjus, one
<lb/>does not need to strongly press it in the hand;
<lb/>Note the last [point on] verjus: shortly after, [it] spoils the
<lb/>colors, this is why it is effaced [above]:
<lb/>Note, that all of the earthenware pots, must be 
<lb/>new, and very clean, next take
<lb/>care about this ,.~~~
<lb/>Note✠ ✠
<lb/>The cambric being quite dry, one plunges it
<lb/>into the fish glue. One needs not to
<lb/>take more glue than that the first
<lb/>colors should be well moistened; one does the same
<lb/>with pale colors as well. The cambric being
<lb/>quite dry, one polishes them with the hand, from
<lb/>both sides, and one folds them, each color inside
<lb/>a white paper. And when one wants to use
<lb/>them, one takes only one or two pieces of them at
<lb/>a time. ~~~~ Note: as I said before this,
<lb/>that the cords must be of
<lb/>horsehair in order to not attach, with the pins the cambrics
<lb/>to the cord.
<lb/>Note, the most favourable weather, for ~
<lb/>dyeing pink, and like [this] too ~
<lb/>all the other colors, even also for washing
</ab>

<pb facs="#f030"/>
<ab>
<lb/>and printing parchment, is the month of
<lb/>May, or just as well the start of the month of
<lb/>June, and like [this] too, the start of the month of + August and
<lb/>of September, also for making velum green,
<lb/>or otherwise said, parchment. ~~
<lb/>Way to wash the velum. One needs to
<lb/>put to soak in the evening, and the next day, one
<lb/>washes it, as one washes the laundry, piece by piece,
<lb/>in rain water or fountain water, entirely
<lb/>cold, without ever heating it. Nor
<lb/>for the soaking, because the velum or parchment,
<lb/>will become as easy to tear
<lb/>as paper in heating the water. One washes it
<lb/>in this way, twice a day, changing
<lb/>the water each time, and this thusly eight days in
<lb/>a row. But when the parchment is written [upon] with
<lb/>red letters, one needs to scrape the said letter. After ~
<lb/>having washed the parchment, two or three days, one
<lb/>takes it out of the water, and one spreads it out on a
<lb/>very smooth board, all wet like it is, one scrapes the
<lb/>red letters with the sharp edge of a pen-knife or a knife,
<lb/>grating [it]. One needs to hold one's hand very lightly, and
<lb/>turn the parchment on both sides. If there are ~
<lb/>red letters there too, one needs to scrape so well that one
<lb/>cannot see anything of the red, because the green doesn't have enough strength
<lb/>to cover the red, nor musical notes,
<lb/>as it is not appropriate for making green. . ~~~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f033"/>
<ab>
<lb/>After the parchment, is scraped one
<lb/>throws them into water immediately, next being well
<lb/>washed, and eight days have passed, if the water remains
<lb/>clear it is a sign that it is washed enough. ~~
<lb/>Next one takes it outside of the water, pressing it
<lb/>in the hand as much as one can, and one
<lb/>spreads it, well polished, on top of a piece of 
<lb/>coverlet; and one applies immediately on ~
<lb/>leaves from the garden, with the underside on top of the
<lb/>velum; this being done, one puts there a board on top
<lb/>of the same size as a board
<lb/>suitable for this work, next one puts there again
<lb/>another piece of coverlet on the said
<lb/>board, then some parchment, and some leaves,
<lb/>all as the first board, one continues this
<lb/>five, or six, boards one on the other, if
<lb/>one wants it, but at the last board one puts there
<lb/>on top very heavy weights, [for] the time of
<lb/>seven or eight days, ~~~
<lb/>Note when the parchment is removed from the
<lb/>pass, and it is not well printed
<lb/>everywhere, one wets with a piece of sponge
<lb/>the place that is not well printed, as
<lb/>closely as one can, but one needs to take care that
<lb/>the water does not run on the velum, next one
</ab>

<pb facs="#f034"/>
<ab>
<lb/>applies the flowers from the garden on top, and
<lb/>one does as here before, one does this 
<lb/>only, for one day, or two, after the parchment
<lb/>is outside of the pass, because the pieces
<lb/>of coverlet must be hung in the open air,
<lb/>when one does not have the convenience of having the
<lb/>pieces, one takes the whole entire coverlet,
<lb/>half-worn, better more worn than less; but
<lb/>when the coverlet is entirely worn, one
<lb/>folds it in two to make use of it. ~~
<lb/>In removing the parchment from the pass one
<lb/>needs to leave it to dry on the board, and
<lb/>next remove the leaves, ~~~
<lb/>Another way to dry the velum, after
<lb/>having washed it, without wanting to print it, one
<lb/>takes it out of the water, and one lays it flat immediately on
<lb/>the board, very clean. ~~~
<lb/>To make green, one needs to take a
<lb/>quarter [pound] of verdigris; it must be well ~
<lb/>ground, one puts it in the evening, in a cruet
<lb/>very clean, next put there a little water, and
<lb/>mix it like this very well, next put there again a little water
<lb/>such that the water does not overpower the verdigris
<lb/>at all, one leaves it to soak thus all
<lb/>night, the next day, one sprinkles on top
</ab>

<pb facs="#f035"/>
<ab>
<lb/>∞ one ounce of white tartar, well
<lb/>ground + + and for two liards ground alum next one pours very gently
<lb/>three pints of rain, or fountain, water
<lb/>in pouring the water on top of the green, one needs to 
<lb/>stir well with a little wooden palette knife,
<lb/>with a long handle
<lb/>+ that one makes for this end, from there, one puts it
<lb/>to boil and one continues to stir it, until
<lb/>such time that the green starts to boil, very
<lb/>strongly; one needs to always take care, to not ~
<lb/>trap the vapor of the fumes that escape
<lb/>from the green; because it is venom; one 
<lb/>leaves it to boil + + stirring always until such time as it is reduced
<lb/>roughly by half; next ~
<lb/>one leaves it to cool, then one passes
<lb/>it through a very white cloth; like
<lb/>one does cheese, pouring one needs to
<lb/>take care not to move the bottom, but
<lb/>when the bright green is all poured [out], and 
<lb/>bottled in a bottle, with three or four
<lb/>spoons reserved, more or less
<lb/>that one leaves in the cruet, to stir
<lb/>with the bottom, being well stirred, one 
<lb/>passes it also through the same cloth, in a
<lb/>dish all by itself, this green is useful for greening
<lb/>the stems of flowers.
<lb/>Note, the earthenware cruet,
<lb/>can never be used for another thing, _
<lb/>it is necessary that it be new; and kept for
<lb/>that [use]
</ab>

<pb facs="#f036"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Way to green the stems of flowers,
<lb/>one puts in a dish, a good spoon
<lb/>of little white, like the painter +uses, for the firstcolor + that one mixes with
<lb/>clear/white gum, for this end, one ~
<lb/>puts it to soak five or six days in advance, a
<lb/>large handful of gum, as much as one can hold in one hand, better more, than less;
<lb/>before mixing the little white one passes
<lb/>the gum, through a very white cloth, like
<lb/>I said for the green, next one mixes with,
<lb/>two, or three spoons, of very white gamboge,
<lb/>then one pours the green on top, and the
<lb/>rest of the gum also, but when the thick
<lb/>green, is not sufficient, to green well, one
<lb/>pours some green from the bottle; until such time
<lb/>that the whole is just as you wish, next
<lb/>one leaves it to become thick like pap,
<lb/>stirring it two, or three times, each day,
<lb/>this having been done; one applies it on the stems
<lb/>of flowers, with a paintbrush, the stems being
<lb/>dry, if they are not even, one paints them
<lb/>with the paintbrush, once more, and that
<lb/>several times, if there is need. but once is best;
<lb/>and if the stems do not shine
<lb/>enough at all to your
<lb/>wishes one needs to pass over with the paintbrush of egg white, well beaten; ~~~
<lb/>One does the same way, for the stems of
<lb/>carnations, and that without using gamboge,
</ab>

<pb facs="#f037"/>
<ab>
<lb/>otherwise only five, or six drops, one needs to
<lb/>always watch, to not ever pour yellow
<lb/>over green, but aptly green over yellow. ~
<lb/>Way to dye velum, or parchment,
<lb/>for carnations, one puts in a little dish,
<lb/>five, or six drops of gamboge, very clear,
<lb/>like for stems, of the said flowers, next
<lb/>one pours on top while stirring, the green from the
<lb/>bottle, half, or the three parts of a
<lb/>dish, that done, one takes a little piece
<lb/>of sponge, one wets the end of it in this soup,
<lb/>and one passes it over the velum, rather
<lb/>thinly, then one leaves it to dry, next one
<lb/>greens it again once more, and that, three, or four
<lb/>times, in succession, that done, and being
<lb/>very dry, one turns it on its other side,
<lb/>and one does the same thing, if one sees after
<lb/>that, that the velum, is green enough, one leaves it
<lb/>to dry again well, next one plunges a
<lb/>piece of sponge, very clean, in some egg
<lb/>white, well beaten, and one passes over the velum
<lb/>rather thinly also, but one needs to do one's [best as]
<lb/>possible, that the velum, is everywhere, very
<lb/>wet, being well dried, one turns it
<lb/>to its other side, and one does the same, it
</ab>

<pb facs="#f038"/>
<ab>
<lb/>is enough, to do that one time, on each
<lb/>side.
<lb/>note, that one needs, to green, the parchment,
<lb/>and the paper, five, or 6. times, on each side, to be good
<lb/>Way, to green velum, or parchment,
<lb/>for rose leaves, les alimons, ranunculus,
<lb/>and other flowers, one does as I said, here
<lb/>before, but in place of five, or six drops,
<lb/>of gamboge, one takes the amount of two
<lb/>little spoons of the said gamboge, more, or less,
<lb/>hauling up as much as one wants to have the yellow-green,
<lb/>but the yellow must be very bright.
<lb/>green paper is made in the same way also,
<lb/>Green paper, again is made, in this
<lb/>way, one takes cauliflower leaves,
<lb/>one removes the ribs, from there one pounds them in
<lb/>a mortar, then one puts them in a little
<lb/>sac, next, one puts the said sac, in
<lb/>a press, with a saucer beneath to ~
<lb/>receive the soup, but if one does not have a press,
<lb/>one wrings the little cloth sack with the hands,
<lb/>as + + hard as one can, one takes a pint
<lb/>of this soup, and one stirs in the said
<lb/>soup a half quarter [of a pound], of verdigris
<lb/>well pestled; and if one wants, after the green ~
<lb/>is well ground, one passes it again through a
</ab>

<pb facs="#f039"/>
<ab>
<lb/>sieve, this being done, before putting it into the
<lb/>soup; the verdigris, being well mixed ~
<lb/>and stirred in the said soup one puts it three
<lb/>or four hours in the sun, next ~
<lb/>one takes a little piece of sponge, and one ~
<lb/>greens the paper in the same way, as
<lb/>the preceding green. one needs to move the bottom, from time,
<lb/>note: if there is no sun, one skips this step; to time. ~
<lb/>Red paper is made in the same way
<lb/>also, one takes clear gum, with a
<lb/>little + half packet of vermillion, that one mixes well
<lb/>together, the vermillion being well mixed, one
<lb/>pours once more a little half spoon, of the
<lb/>said gum, with two or three spoonfuls of water,
<lb/>one needs to stir the whole together well, next
<lb/>one leaves it like that, two, or three hours
<lb/>more, or less, before using it, ✠ then
<lb/>one reddens the paper with it, one needs to move the
<lb/>bottom, before reddening, and the second time that
<lb/>one reddens the paper, one needs to pass the sponge
<lb/>very lightly, and do one's [best] possible in order that
<lb/>the paper will be beautiful red enough, being reddened
<lb/>twice on each side,. one passes over it also,
<lb/>twice on each side, egg white, very 
<lb/>lightly ; But for green paper ; and yellow, etc.
<lb/>It suffices to pass over, with the egg ~
<lb/>white, on each side, once. ~~~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f040"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note, red paper, is made again,
<lb/>in this way; one takes a packet of
<lb/>vermillion, or the amount of a mussel
<lb/>shell,; with two mussel shells, of
<lb/>minium, this is a coarse red dyestuff;
<lb/>that is why, one needs to rub it well
<lb/>on the marble; before mixing it
<lb/>with the vermillion; after that one needs to take
<lb/>clear gum, and vermillion, and 
<lb/>minium, being mixed together in a dish, one
<lb/>needs to pour a little of this clear gum
<lb/>on top, and one mixes well together the two
<lb/>dyes with a little stick, the dye being
<lb/>well mixed; one needs to pour in the dye a
<lb/>half glass of water, one needs to stir it all well
<lb/>together; and after one needs to take a =
<lb/>note without gum, water only [suffices] for 
<lb/>making paper
</ab>

<pb facs="#f041"/>
<ab>
<lb/>little piece of sponge, and redden the paper with [it];
<lb/>one needs to do your [best] possible, in order that the paper
<lb/>becomes beautiful red enough, being reddened two times,
<lb/>on each side; one passes over it also, being
<lb/>dry, with a little piece of sponge the egg
<lb/>white; very lightly, two times on each
<lb/>size; the egg white, must be well beaten, before
<lb/>you use it; and that generally for all
<lb/>the colors, that you make with [it]; ~~
<lb/>Note when you see, that the dye becomes
<lb/>too thick, one needs to pour a little water on top;
<lb/>and do like that from time, to time; if you
<lb/>find it necessary; one needs to do that also
<lb/>with paper made with vermillion alone;
<lb/>Note at this ✠ that which is written in the nine
<lb/>first lines, to make paper red with 
<lb/>vermillion; that is for painting flowers on
<lb/>paper, and that without using egg white; but
<lb/>for making paper red with vermillion alone;
<lb/>one needs to do all as it is [described,] mixed, with minium◆
</ab>

<pb facs="#f042"/>
<ab>
<lb/>For making paper yellow, one takes the
<lb/>size of two, or three big nuts, of
<lb/>gamboge that one puts to soak in a little
<lb/>pot with fountain, or rain, water ~
<lb/>and that [is] the quantity for covering in yellow
<lb/>well, and a bit on top [of that]; one puts there also
<lb/>to soak for five, or six liards, of saffron,
<lb/>whole, without being pestled, being well soaked
<lb/>one could boil it if one wanted, next
<lb/>one pours a little of this soup, in the
<lb/>gamboge, which one mixes well together; from there
<lb/>one yellows the paper, but if one sees that the ~
<lb/>paper is not beautiful, or high yellow enough, one ~
<lb/>there pours again some saffron soup, until such
<lb/>time as, that the whole is to your liking, but
<lb/>when the soup is too thick, one needs to put there
<lb/>a little more water, the paper yellowed two
<lb/>times, on each side, when the colors are good;
<lb/>makes a very beautiful paper,
<lb/>and even once also; ~
<lb/>note that the egg white must
<lb/>be well beaten before
<lb/>you use it; ~
<lb/>Way for accommodating dye, for 
<lb/>painting flowers on paper, gamboge ~
<lb/>mixes itself, and one puts it to soak in the same
<lb/>way, as I said here before, but instead of
<lb/>taking so large a quantity of gamboge, one
<lb/>only puts to soak the size of one + big nut; and
<lb/>water. In hauling it out; next one traces with the
<lb/>paintbrush, without the use of saffron. ~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f045"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Vermillion is mixed, with clear
<lb/>gum, being well mixed, one pours on top a
<lb/>little bit of water, and some drops of gum ~
<lb/>then on leaves it, two, or three hours, like that,
<lb/>next one paints, with the paintbrush, on paper,
<lb/>but when the vermillion becomes too thick, one needs
<lb/>always to thin it with a little water, and some ~
<lb/>clear gum. ~~~
<lb/>Carmine is mixed, as I have said here before,
<lb/>on the fourth folio, at the beginning of this
<lb/>book, at this mark * one returns the folio,
<lb/>and one sees the way, to mix the blue that
<lb/>one calls the ashes of England, this dye is used,
<lb/>for painting blue flowers, and violet also,
<lb/>for that, it is sufficient to pass the red paintbrush, over the blue flower
<lb/>For accommodating the green, for painting leaves
<lb/>and stems of flowers on paper, or parchment,
<lb/>one takes some prepared verdigris, the
<lb/>amount of one half ounce, more, or less, 
<lb/>hauling it up  such that  one wants much, or less to trace, one
<lb/>puts it to soak in a little, pot, with a
<lb/>little vinegar, it suffices when the vinegar,
<lb/>is a little on top of the green, next one ~
<lb/>leaves it to soak for one day, and one night, from there
<lb/>one uses it with the paintbrush, plunging it
<lb/>each time, a little in the thickness of the dye,
<lb/>when the dye becomes too thick, one needs there
</ab>

<pb facs="#f046"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note when you don't want to buy the green
<lb/>at the painter's; ~ ✠ ✠ ✠ .. to this line, read
<lb/>Behold the way that one needs to prepare it;
<lb/>one needs to take a half quarter [of a pound]; or an ounce,
<lb/>of verdigris, it must be well pounded, then
<lb/>pass it through a thick little sieve; then one needs to rub it,
<lb/>with some clear gum, and a few drops of vinegar;
<lb/>on top of a marble slab, or of sandstone; being rubbed
<lb/>enough; one needs to put it in a little pot, and thin
<lb/>it with some vinegar; and from time, to time, stretch it
<lb/>always like that; putting in some times some
<lb/>drops of gum, without ever putting water in it;
<lb/>because vinegar is the best
<lb/>after that you use it with the paintbrush, for tracing
<lb/>on paper, etc. ~~~
<lb/>But when you want to have the green a little more
<lb/>brown, one needs to put there a little more of the gum; ~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f047"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note, again another way, for the same red;
<lb/>✠ Take for one patard of brazil wood, and for
<lb/>two liards alum, with two pints of old beer, the older,
<lb/>is the best; leave that to boil together, until [reduced by]
<lb/>half; next one passes the soup through a clear
<lb/>linen cloth, and one pours it into a bottle; and when
<lb/>one wants to use it, and paint with it; one pours
<lb/>of this red dye, into a mussel shell, or
<lb/>just as well into an oyster shell, and leave it like that
<lb/>5. or 6. hours. and if you can put it several
<lb/>hours in the sun, the dye will be ready sooner to 
<lb/>use, provided that the sun is not too ardent;
<lb/>for the dye would be in little time, too diminished, and
<lb/>dry in the shell; after that, one needs to pour off the clear [liquid] into
<lb/>another shell very clean also, and some hours later,
<lb/>again pour it into another shell; one needs to continue
<lb/>like this, two or three times, if there is need; for when the
<lb/>dye becomes a little thick, this marks [the point that] it is good for tracing
<lb/>on cambric, and on paper; you can test with the
<lb/>paintbrush if the color is good, for your use; Note,
<lb/>In the same way also one readies, or prepares the color
<lb/>violet; but instead of brazil wood; one needs to take some
<lb/>logwood; Note that one needs for it to be good beer, without
<lb/>being mixed, when it will be ten. and 20. years old) One makes
<lb/>red paper of this also, with the two reds, and some violet also ~~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f048"/>
<ab>
<lb/>to pour a little vinegar, and sometimes
<lb/>also a little water, instead of vinegar, but
<lb/>the first time, one needs to always put to soak
<lb/>with the vinegar, and five, or six drops, 
<lb/>of clear gum, one buys the verdigris
<lb/>prepared, at the painter's, saying that the
<lb/>said green, is for painting on paper, such that it
<lb/>does not have to be prepared, with oil; ~
<lb/>✠ ✠ ✠ ..
<lb/>Another way again, to make 
<lb/>red for painting, on paper, one ~
<lb/>takes a quarter [of a pound] of brazil wood, with
<lb/>two pintes of vinegar, and a half quarter
<lb/>[of a pound] of alum, one leaves it to boil like that, until
<lb/>[reduced by] half, next, one passes the soup through a
<lb/>linen cloth, and one pours it, into a bottle,
<lb/>this lasts for three years, well, for your
<lb/>use, ~~~~~~ read to this ✠
<lb/>But when one wants, to paint with the
<lb/>said red, one pours of this red, into a
<lb/>mussel shell, or just as well, into an oyster
<lb/>shell, one needs to put it in the sun
<lb/>for the space of seven, or eight hours, next
<lb/>one pours off the clear [liquid] into another ~
<lb/>shell, very clean also; and the next day
</ab>

<pb facs="#f049"/>
<ab>
<lb/>one pours it again into another, if
<lb/>there is need, but when the sun
<lb/>does not shine, one puts the shell on a
<lb/>chafing dish very tepid, and next one does as
<lb/>here before, then one plunges the paintbrush into
<lb/>the dye, and one traces on the paper
<lb/>with [it], for seeing if the color is good,
<lb/>but, if one sees, that the color is not
<lb/>good yet, and a little thick, one needs to
<lb/>wait one day longer to use it,
<lb/>next one does one's best to
<lb/>use this dye in a day, or two,
<lb/>because it becomes too thick to 
<lb/>use, so much that one is obligated, to
<lb/>pour into it two, or three drops of water, and that
<lb/>is why the dye traced upon
<lb/>the paper, passes very easily, and
<lb/>also does not last too long, ~~
<lb/>In the same way also, one
<lb/>readies the color violet, but instead
<lb/>of brazil wood, one needs to take,
<lb/>logwood. ~~~
<lb/>The way for melting silk gum, as
<lb/>here before; return four folios; ~~~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f050"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Way of dyeing silk, of damask + and
<lb/>satin, if the white silk, is not
<lb/>well cleaned, and very soiled, or with
<lb/>stains, one needs to wash it with cold
<lb/>rain water, and some white soap, or
<lb/>just as well with soap, as one washes the
<lb/>linens + + but the white soap is better next one rinses it, and one
<lb/>dries it; next, being dry, if this [is] for staying
<lb/>white, one mixes in the silk gum, a little
<lb/>pale blue starch, one needs to make the rest as follows ◆
<lb/>Red dye, and violet, for silk,
<lb/>is boiled, as I said here before, one needs to
<lb/>put the silk inside, and leave it to boil well,
<lb/>from there one takes the silk, out of the soup
<lb/>with a stick, one opens it up and one hangs it
<lb/>on cords, being dry, one washes the
<lb/>said silk in a soapy wash of white soap,
<lb/>for brightening it, being washed, one
<lb/>rinses it in rain water, and one
<lb/>hangs it on cord, ✠ being dry: one
<lb/>applies it, on a board, next
<lb/>~one dries it, from there one irons it
<lb/>as one does the linens,. Note
<lb/>this ✠ mark three lines above,
<lb/>✠ being dry: one needs to starch it with
</ab>

<pb facs="#f051"/>
<ab>
<lb/>silk gum, being well gummed,
<lb/>one applies it on a board, one [has] the
<lb/>task of polishing it also as evenly as one
<lb/>can, next one hangs it on cords, being
<lb/>quasi dry, one irons it with an
<lb/>iron as one irons the linens. ~~
<lb/>Note, if one does not want, to have the ~
<lb/>silk so red brown, instead of vinegar
<lb/>one needs to make the dye boil with
<lb/>some rain water, + + but two pints of old beer is better still; the silk being well~
<lb/>boiled, one takes it out of the dye, and one
<lb/>hangs it on cord; after that, one can soak it again in the soup;
<lb/>and throws it, bing dry, in the soapy wash, it ~
<lb/>must be cold, without ever warming it,
<lb/>but if all the colors are good, to one's liking, one must not 
<lb/>wash it at all, in any way.... ~~~~~
<lb/>Like [this] also for washing all sorts
<lb/>of taffeta, the water should never be hot,
<lb/>one washes all sorts of colors, as
<lb/>one washes white taffeta, one needs to
<lb/>leave [it] to soak for one day, and one night, being
<lb/>very well soaped, before washing it, then
<lb/>one washes it also as clean as one can,
<lb/>and one does as the white taffeta, but without blue in the
<lb/>silk gum; ~
<lb/>Violet silk, is made in the same
</ab>

<pb facs="#f052"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note jonquil cloth, and other paler yellow
<lb/>colors; are made as one makes with silk, or
<lb/>taffeta, and white satin; being clean and tidy,
<lb/>and well dried as well; one needs to put to soak in the
<lb/>dye, etc. but when it is boiled enough, and that the color
<lb/>is good; one needs to take [it] out of the dye, and and press
<lb/>the dye out well; next if you like, or if you find it
<lb/>good, after having tested plunging a few pieces in the
<lb/>verjus, and by that, that the color is more agreeable, to your
<lb/>liking +  but it is not lasting with the verjus, it changes colors + put also piece, by piece, opening it up well
<lb/>in the verjus, all the rest of the cambric, muslin,
<lb/>and cloth that you have boiled in the dye; after
<lb/>that; after having pressed it, and opened two or three times, in
<lb/>the verjus, as one does the pink colors, one needs to
<lb/>press out the verjus well; immediately next, one needs
</ab>

<pb facs="#f053"/>
<ab>
<lb/>throw it in the soapy wash of white soap; next one
<lb/>washes it as clear, as one sees to be enough, then one 
<lb/>needs to rinse it, in two rain waters, at the last
<lb/>one needs to press the water out well; from there, dry it; and
<lb/>being dry; one needs to plunge it well, and stiffen it in
<lb/>hide glue; after that one needs to hang it in the attic
<lb/>on a horsehair cord, and that as evenly as you can
<lb/>one needs to take good care that the end, and the rest does not stick
<lb/>together, for when it is dry, you would have to
<lb/>tear it to detach one from the other; one does not need to
<lb/>press the hide glue strongly out of your cambric etc. but 
<lb/>leave it a little well wet; one needs to do the same with all
<lb/>the colors you make with [it]; the same also with fish
<lb/>glue; Note, when you would like to have a more
<lb/>heightened color still, than the jonquil color, instead of leaving it to soak
<lb/>for half an hour; one needs to leave it to soak three quarters of an hour, and one needs
<lb/>to leave it to boil a longer time also; but if this is for making flowers;
<lb/>gamboge, and saffron, is better still; as here above;
</ab>

<pb facs="#f054"/>
<ab>
<lb/>way also, as one dyes red silk,
<lb/>but instead of brazil wood,
<lb/>one takes logwood~~
<lb/>Note, that beer, cannot be too old, when it is twelve, and
<lb/>20. years old; and it is much better, than vinegar, and rain water;~
<lb/>Way for jonquil silk, and cloth,
<lb/>one needs to take a half quarter [of a pound]
<lb/>of baker's chamomile + + and for three liards of pounded alum that one makes boil
<lb/>with two pints of rain water; one puts
<lb/>the silk to soak + + in the dye round-about a half quarter
<lb/>of an hour, next one makes it boil together,
<lb/>being a little boiled; one takes the
<lb/>silk, or cloth out of the dye; + + for seeing if it is good one
<lb/>presses it with the hands, and one throws it into
<lb/>a soapy wash of white soap + if it is good; in-following one
<lb/>washes it, as clear, as one sees to be enough,
<lb/>then one needs to rinse it with rain
<lb/>water, and press the water out well, from there one
<lb/>needs to + + make it dry, and after that stiffen it, with silk gum, well
<lb/>soaked, and strongly thick, next one applies it
<lb/>on a board, as evenly as one can,
<lb/>one on top of the other, from there one hangs it on a cord,
<lb/>being dry, one irons it as one
<lb/>does linens., ∞ Note, for making flowers
<lb/>of cambric, one needs
<lb/>never to iron anything, with the iron;
<lb/>Way for having a paler yellow,
<lb/>it suffices to put the silk, in the dye
</ab>

<pb facs="#f057"/>
<ab>
<lb/>to soak a little, after that one needs to make it boil, and
<lb/>when the dye starts to boil;
<lb/>being a little boiled, one takes it out
<lb/>of the dye, and one does as I 
<lb/>said here before, about brown yellow, jonquil ~~~
<lb/>Cloth that one dyes yellow like
<lb/>silk, at the last rinse, after having
<lb/>pressed the water out well, one can put them in
<lb/>verjus, if one wants, and if one sees that
<lb/>the color is more beautiful to one's liking, also
<lb/>the verjus, one can continue that, each
<lb/>time that one dyes, but if one sees that the
<lb/>color is not more beautiful with the verjus, it
<lb/>is not necessary to use it, because the
<lb/>cambric is in peril of sticking to itself [of staining itself??], and of
<lb/>changing color, next one dries
<lb/>it, being dry, one stiffens it with 
<lb/>fish glue, and just as well with
<lb/>hide glue, if it is for making flowers;
<lb/>being dry, one irons it with the hands
<lb/>only; if not, one needs to iron it like
<lb/>silk. ~~~
<lb/>Cloth that one dyes yellow like silk; being
<lb/>soaked a half hour, or three quarters of an hour; being well boiled,
<lb/>and the color to your liking; one needs to press the dye out well,
<lb/>next one needs to open it up well, and plunge it into the verjus, if
<lb/>you find it good; then press the verjus out well, and
<lb/>throw it also into the soapy wash of white soap; being well
<lb/>washed to your liking, one needs to rinse it in two, or three,
<lb/>other rain, or fountain, waters, at the last, one
<lb/>needs to press out the water well; then one hangs it in the attic
<lb/>with the window closed; being dry; one plunges them,
<lb/>and stiffens [them] in the hide glue; but one does not need
<lb/>to press the glue, as strongly as the water; but the cambric etc.
<lb/>must be a little well wet; as I said here before,
<lb/>then one hangs it again once more in the attic, with the
<lb/>window closed, all as one did with all the other
<lb/>colors; being dry; if it is for making flowers, one 
<lb/>needs to polish it with the hands only; then fold
<lb/>them, and put them in a paper; one needs to do
<lb/>like that also, with all the colors that you make,
<lb/>for making flowers; B when it is not for making
<lb/>flowers with, one needs always to iron it all with
<lb/>an iron as one irons linens; ~
<lb/>Red cloth, and violet, is made as
<lb/>red silk, and violet, but instead of
<lb/>vinegar, one can take rain water
</ab>

<pb facs="#f058"/>
<ab>
<lb/>if one finds it good, for otherwise
<lb/>vinegar is good also, one needs to stiffen it
<lb/>and do in all things, as yellow cloth.
<lb/>this sort of cloth, is not good for
<lb/>making flowers. ~~~ 
<lb/>the old beer, is better still,
<lb/>when it is 8. and 20. years old;
<lb/>but it must be good beer, it must not be small beer;
<lb/>W for making fish glue
<lb/>one needs to take a half quarter [of a pound]
<lb/>of fish glue, one needs to beat it well
<lb/>with a hammer, being well cleared away
<lb/>one cuts it, into little pieces, next
<lb/>one takes three pints of rain, or fountain, water,
<lb/>better less, than more; from there
<lb/>one puts it to soak for one day, after that :+:
<lb/>:+: one puts it to boil in a pot or just as well
<lb/>in an earthenware cruet very tidy, and ~
<lb/>new without having been used for another thing,
<lb/>one needs to stir it strongly often, in order
<lb/>that the glue doesn't burn at the bottom du
<lb/>of the pot, one needs to leave it to boil, until
<lb/>the time, that the water is diminished by around
<lb/>half, one takes a few drops
<lb/>balling it with he fingers, for seeing, if the
<lb/>soup, is thick enough, if it attaches
<lb/>to the fingers, next one takes it off the fire, and
<lb/>one passes it immediately through a linen cloth, into
</ab>

<pb facs="#f059"/>
<ab>
<lb/>another terrine, when the glue ~
<lb/>becomes congealed, one needs always to uncongeal it
<lb/>over a chafing dish, before stiffening the
<lb/>cambric with [it], one needs to do the same
<lb/>also, with hide glue, ~~
<lb/>Way for making hide ~
<lb/>glue, one needs to take a half pound
<lb/>of white leather, as one cuts lanyards,
<lb/>the little pieces which fall from it
<lb/>only, ) when one goes to buy it, one
<lb/>needs to always explain, that it is for ~
<lb/>making hide glue with, and
<lb/>qu'but one needs to avoid taking the ~
<lb/>little pieces of red leather, or just as well yellow,
<lb/>or blue, because that spoils the glue, to stiffen
<lb/>cambric for making flowers; one needs
<lb/>to wash the leather, as clean as one can,
<lb/>next one needs to take it out of the water,
<lb/>and press the water out, next one takes two + + or three
<lb/>pints of water + + rather more than less + in an earthenware pot, from there
<lb/>one puts the leather immediately in the said water,
<lb/>next one + + puts it on a chafing dish + + or foot stove
</ab>

<pb facs="#f060"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note at this mark ) the little pieces that fall from shoes,
<lb/>white, and from the white linings of shoes; all these little pieces
<lb/>there, are very good for that also; but one needs to put the leather to soak
<lb/>for one day; before washing it; Note when the glue is made, and that
<lb/>the leather is pressed a little out of the glue; you can the leather
<lb/>once more into the same earthenware pot, with three [illeg.] ∞
<lb/>[illeg.] ~o~ pints of water; rather [illeg.]less, than [illeg.]more; one needs to let it draw [itself out]; 
<lb/>all like the first glue; one needs to put it over the fire; but
<lb/>without ever boiling, from the morning, all the way until the next
<lb/>morning; one needs do the same also, with the first glue =
</ab>

<pb facs="#f061"/>
<ab>
<lb/>after that; one needs to pass it through a linen cloth also, and
<lb/>mix it with the first glue; next one needs to stiffen, and
<lb/>make colors with [it], as you wish to do; But
<lb/>before passing either one through the linen cloth, one needs to leave it
<lb/>to cool, to see if it is congealed enough, such that one could
<lb/>cut it with a knife; if that is not [the case], one needs to again
<lb/>leave it to draw [itself out] over the fire; all until such time that it is good; but the 2.nd 
<lb/>glue is not ordinarily as strong, as the first, that is why,
<lb/>one needs to mix them together; But when you have need of a greater
<lb/>quantity, instead of a half pound; one needs to take a pound of leather,
<lb/>and more still if there is need; and one needs to take water by hauling it out;
<lb/>one needs to do the same, with fish glue also; ~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f062"/>
<ab>
<lb/>one needs to take care to note let it boil,
<lb/>next, one leaves it to draw [itself out], like that on
<lb/>the chafing dish + + or foot stove until such time that the soup becomes
<lb/>thick, and that it sticks to the finger, and that it is
<lb/>congealed, that done, one puts it to heat, to
<lb/>de-congeal it, then, one takes the leather out of the
<lb/>soup, fo press it with the hands, until such
<lb/>time that the soup is a little outside of [the leather], next
<lb/>one passes the said soup through a linen cloth, and
<lb/>one stiffens the cambric with [it], one needs to
<lb/>maintain always the temperature, in order that the
<lb/>cambric, and the glue do not congeal
<lb/>in the hands at all, one needs to plunge only two
<lb/>or three pieces at a time, and hang them immediately,
<lb/>to avoid this inconvenience, the cambric being
<lb/>dry, if one sees that it is too stiff to
<lb/>use, before plunging other pieces
<lb/>of cambric, one needs to pour into the glue
<lb/>three or four, spoons of water, more or less
<lb/>according to the quantity of glue that one sees,
<lb/>but the best is, not to put water in the glue, since the stuffs,
<lb/>or cambric becomes [too] pliable after . . . 
<lb/>Note, that one must never pour water,
<lb/>into fish glue, ~~~~
<lb/>I misspoke, here above, as you can see; ~~~
<lb/>Way for undyeing pink color
</ab>

<pb facs="#f063"/>
<ab>
<lb/>when it is spoiled, one needs to boil it
<lb/>with lye made from vine ash,
<lb/>the lye must be strongly clear,
<lb/>next one puts the cambric inside, and one
<lb/>makes it boil, until such time as the cambric
<lb/>is well white, next one takes it from the fire
<lb/>all boiling, immediately one takes a stick,
<lb/>and one removes the cambric, one needs to throw them ~
<lb/>immediately into a bucket of rain or fountain water,
<lb/>being rinsed, one throws it again
<lb/>into another bucket of water, from there one ~
<lb/>puts it to whiten one day, and one night, next
<lb/>one rinses it, lightly with the hand without rubbing,
<lb/>the other rinses must be made in the same
<lb/>way also, next one needs to dry it,
<lb/>and when one makes the lye one ~
<lb/>needs to tie it up it a little, and put it
<lb/>to boil, and whiten, with the fine linens, being
<lb/>dry, this cambric can be used for dyeing
<lb/>all sorts of colors, but for dyeing
<lb/>pink one needs to always choose the
<lb/>whitest cambric that one has,
<lb/>Blue color, dyed with moss/lichen?, is
<lb/>undyed in the same way also, as
</ab>

<pb facs="#f064"/>
<ab>
<lb/>well as jonquil colors, and yellow, dyed
<lb/>with baker's chamomile. ~~~
<lb/>But jonquil cambric, and yellow dyed
<lb/>with gamboge do not undye, but
<lb/>when it is spoiled, or just as well not beautiful
<lb/>enough to use, one can dye it
<lb/>red, with vermillion, and fish
<lb/>glue, or with hide glue.
<lb/>return here above to the 3. folio, at the beginning.
<lb/>Blue dyed with brown, and
<lb/>pale starch blue, cambric is undyed
<lb/>with very hot water, the amount of a
<lb/>pint, one needs to change it in three or
<lb/>four hot waters, and one rinses it one
<lb/>time in cold water, next one pours
<lb/>all the water together stirring them ~
<lb/>vigorously while pouring, in order that the blue will be ~
<lb/>all amassed in one water, next one ~
<lb/>leaves this water one hour, or two, without
<lb/>moving it, in order that the blue is all fallen ~
<lb/>to the bottom, then one pours the water all
<lb/>gently taking care to [not] move the bottom, but
<lb/>at the end, when one sees that the blue
<lb/>comes with the water, before throwing it all away
</ab>

<pb facs="#f065"/>
<ab>
<lb/>one needs to leave it to fall again to the
<lb/>bottom, from there to throw all the water away; this
<lb/>blue can be used again, as before;
<lb/>Note that one never undyes this blue
<lb/>cambric unless one sees that the cambric
<lb/>is too thick to use, because the color
<lb/>is always good, this is why one needs
<lb/>always to take fine cambric, the ~
<lb/>first time, because the blue fattens
<lb/>the stuffs, but when one is forced to
<lb/>undye it, one needs to undy the pale blue
<lb/>alone, and the brown blue alone, in order to
<lb/>make use again of these blues like the
<lb/>first time. ~~~
<lb/>Way for making vine ashes
<lb/>when one cuts the vine one needs to
<lb/>gather up all of the cut wood. One needs to put it
<lb/>to burn in a chimney, or in an oven,
<lb/>very tidy, without wood, and without ashes of
<lb/>other sorts of wood, the vine wood being ~
<lb/>all burnt, one needs to take all the fire, and ~
<lb/>ashes, in a nasty pot, that is worth
</ab>

<pb facs="#f066"/>
<ab>
<lb/>nothing, to be used for another thing, next
<lb/>one needs to keep stoking it, from time,
<lb/>to time, until such time, that the whole, is consumed
<lb/>into ash. ~~~
<lb/>Way for making lye of ~
<lb/>vine ash, one needs to take three
<lb/>double handfuls of ash, with
<lb/>seven or eight pints of rain, or fountain,
<lb/>water, one needs to leave it to boil, until
<lb/>[it reduces to] four, or five pints, all the more,
<lb/>if one boils them in a marmite + + well covered, one must,
<lb/>as soon as the marmite is removed from the fire,
<lb/>pour it into an earthenware pot, very
<lb/>tidy, and having been used for anything else,
<lb/>other than for dyeing pink, one needs
<lb/>to leave the ashes at the bottom of the marmite,
<lb/>as much as one can, next the next day,
<lb/>one needs to pass the lye through a
<lb/>linen cloth, into another pot, pouring
<lb/>it all gently, without moving the ash,
<lb/>which are at the bottom of the pot, from there, one
<lb/>can use it, for all that one 
<lb/>wants to make, with the said lye. ~~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f069"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note the name[s] of dye[s] in Flemish
<lb/>of powdered starch.			powdered starch;
<lb/>of starch paste,. starch paste	|,.	sweet wine / minium [?] .~*
<lb/>brown-blue starch paste.	|	brown-blue 
<lb/>				|	starch paste.
<lb/>pale blue starch paste.	|	pale blue 
<lb/>sweet wine / minium [?].~*	|	starch paste.
<lb/>of gamboge.			|	gamboge.
<lb/>of whole saffron.		|	whole saffron.
<lb/>of vermilion.			|	vermilion.
<lb/>of safflower.			|	safflower.
<lb/>of white wine vinegar.		|	white wine vinegar.
<lb/>of raw tartar.			|	raw white tartar.
<lb/>of leaves of cauliflower,	|	leaves of cauli-
<lb/>without the ribs.  		|	flower, without the
<lb/>				|	ribs.
<lb/>of verdigris.			|	verdigris.
<lb/>of wood of logwood.		|	logwood wood.
<lb/>of Brazilwood.			|	Brazilwood.
<lb/>of ashes of England.		|	English ashes.
<lb/>~Carmine. alum.		|	Carmine. alum.
<lb/>of fish glue.			|	fish glue.
<lb/>of hide glue.			|	hide glue.
<lb/>of ashes, of branches, of	|	ashes of grapevine tendrils.
<lb/>vines				|
</ab>

<pb facs="#f072"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Pattern for painting on
<lb/>paper; note also that this ~
<lb/>little book, must never be
<lb/>given, and not lent, to anyone,
<lb/>outside of our convent of St. Godelieve.
<lb/>IHS	MR
<lb/>This little book, may never be given, ~
<lb/>nor lent, to any ~~~
<lb/>person, outside our cloister of St. Godelieve.
<lb/>Pray for Sister Marie Placida Bens ◆ 1743 ◆
</ab>

<pb facs="#f074"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern
<lb/>IHS MR
<lb/>one needs always, to put all the sorts of flowers
<lb/>that one paints with the holy names of Jesus, and of Maria,
<lb/>put them in a heart, with several pansies around.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f076"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern		pattern
<lb/>IHS
<lb/>on the other side of the picture the holy
<lb/>name of Mary, one must always paint, each
<lb/>side, the one, as the other, equally . . ~~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f078"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Way to gild with gold or silver
<lb/>The only thing that one wants to burnish is gold
<lb/>or silver. One must first prepare the ground
<lb/>with strong glue. Being dry, lay next
<lb/>a layer of lime with white ceruse, paying attention
<lb/>continually that you do not ever lay a second layer
<lb/>unless the first is entirely dry. And do not
<lb/>leave it ever to dry where it is very
<lb/>sunny. And do not lay the white too thickly. One
<lb/>must lay it 9 or 10 times. Then refine [it]
<lb/>and make it very even with a 
<lb/>wolf’s tooth or with water from Spanish
<lb/>soap, and scour it with it until it
<lb/>is even. Next, one must leave it to rest
<lb/>at least one day. Before you go to gild or
<lb/>silver it, only under the gild [areas] one puts
<lb/>the two last coats of glue, some white
<lb/>ceruse, and orange paint, on the ground
<lb/>to have gold color. ~~~~
<lb/>Bile of an eel melted in some brandy
<lb/>is good for illuminating gold or silver
<lb/>in the following colors: green, black, grey,
<lb/>and yellow.
<lb/>It does so that the paint flows, and makes that
<lb/>it does not flake off. This small quantity of
<lb/>gall from an eel is but only for drawing
<lb/>with a paintbrush on little images, but as we make
</ab>

<pb facs="#f081"/>
<ab>
<lb/>larger work, so must one take larger
<lb/>quantities of gall and brandy.
<lb/>Note: if you only wish to make light work,
<lb/>with 4 or 5 ground [layers] to lay
<lb/>it is already enough. ~~~~
<lb/>Note that eel gall is only 
<lb/>for illuminating but not for
<lb/>drawing with a paintbrush on
<lb/>little images. To that end, brandy
<lb/>works well on its own. Also one or two little
<lb/>drops of rainwater or fountain water, this is the best
<lb/>to put in the shell with gold or silver and therewith to
<lb/>gild with foam[?] gold or silver. The
<lb/>ground must be made slightly wet with 
<lb/>well beaten egg white, but overall well wet.
<lb/>Thereafter, one lays the gold or the silver foam thereupon,
<lb/>fine or rough, one puts it down with a small
<lb/>brockskens sponge, well washed beforehand, [and]
<lb/>thereafter squeezed out in a cloth, and thereafter,
<lb/>gilded with. And if the sponge becomes somewhat
<lb/>too dry, one does as before. ~~
<lb/>Note: if it is with oil, one takes ghebrant[drying?]
<lb/>oil and one makes it wet with this oil, and
<lb/>[lays] silver or gold foam thereupon. And one
<lb/>does with the sponge as before. ~~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f084"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern
<lb/>MR
<lb/>the holy name of Jesus, can
<lb/>be painted, on the other side of the picture, in
<lb/>the same way, with the other flowers if there is
<lb/>need . . ~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f086"/>
<ab>
<lb/>each sort of flower must be drawn [(up)] in its branch, and the
<lb/>holy name of Jesus on the other side of the picture, equally
<lb/>MR
</ab>

<pb facs="#f088"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern
<lb/>IHS
<lb/>bouquet for 
<lb/>putting over
<lb/>hearts, which are 
<lb/>filled with
<lb/>wool, one needs
<lb/>to cut each
<lb/>bouquet, holding all of it
<lb/>in its branch, without
<lb/>separating anything, one from the other.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f090"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern
</ab>

<pb facs="#f094"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern
</ab>

<pb facs="#f096"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern
</ab>

<pb facs="#f108"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern
</ab>

<pb facs="#f110"/>
<ab>
<lb/>pattern
<lb/>of a monstrance
<lb/>1757.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f112"/>
<ab>
<lb/>MAR
</ab>

<pb facs="#f128"/>
<ab>
<lb/>St. Augustine
</ab>

<pb facs="#f130"/>
<ab>
<lb/>JESUS, MARY, AUGUSTINE.
<lb/>Since the Holy Spirit allows us to praise, after death, those people who deserve
<lb/>to be praised; it is beyond just, to give a tribute so legitimate to the memory of the
<lb/>REVEREND MOTHER
<lb/>MOTHER ADRIENE TERESE DE MALDEGHEM,
<lb/>Cannonesse Regular of the Order of St. Augustine, who died in Tournai in the Monastery of Our Lady of Sion
<lb/>on the 28th of the year 1680, among the prayers and sorrows of her dear Sisters, after having received the Holy Sacraments of the Church
<lb/>with as much piety, as resignation to the Divine will. 65 years of age, &amp; Professed of her vows for 48, a life that had been as
<lb/>Religious as hers for so many years, could not have promised an ending less Happy: grace
<lb/>perfecting the advantages pulled from her Illustrious Lineage, rendered her a living example of all the virtues,
<lb/>&amp; a subject wholly suited for the governance of others; which was brightly visible throughout her Life, &amp; and in the
<lb/>functions that she exercised as Mistress of the Novices; as Sub-prioress &amp; Prioress with this wise, prudent, steadfast,
<lb/>&amp; Holy Conduct that was inseparable from her character: BUT, following what St Paul said; even though his conscience reproached
<lb/>him with nothing, he was not yet Justified, what Holiness could deliver a person from this healthy fear of the
<lb/>Judgments of God! Thus although we have so many Indications of her eternal happiness, we implore Sacrifices
<lb/>&amp; prayers; Such that if divine Justice should demand of her any remaining expiation in Purgatory, she might as soon as possible
<lb/>be in a state to enjoy the chaste embraces of her heavenly Spouse, These are the charitable services that
<lb/>we demand of the Religious Communities, &amp; of all the faithful.
<lb/>May she rest in peace.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f132"/>
<ab>
<lb/>St Godelieve
<lb/>17 ½   Stone Butter.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f134"/>
<ab>
<lb/>for 3 stuivers, Berlin blue
<lb/>for 3 stuivers, Florentine red
<lb/>for one stuiver, pink[rose?] red
<lb/>for 2 stuivers, blue English ashes
<lb/>for one stuiver, shell white
<lb/>for one stuiver, pale yellow
<lb/>for 2 stuivers, orange dye
<lb/>for one stuiver, borich green
<lb/>six paintbrushes of ortiens[nettles?]
<lb/>for one stuiver, indigo
</ab>

<pb facs="#f136"/>
<ab>
<lb/>does not believe
<lb/>to have the goodness
<lb/>to tiecken[??] from here
<lb/>up to a quarter
<lb/>of it nothing that
<lb/>is of need or of many
<lb/>red alum
<lb/>of co[chineal?]
<lb/>and of tartar
<lb/>I will be fully
<lb/>grateful
</ab>

<pb facs="#f138"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Mr Joris, druggist, sells brazilwood
<lb/>wood that is very good for painting
<lb/>paper red. One does this as follows:
<lb/>for two stuivers’s or five’s worth of
<lb/>this wood according to the puddle that one wants
<lb/>to make. And for the nicest, take but
<lb/>a half of it. And put it in a pot with
<lb/>a can or three pints of rainwater.
<lb/>Let it extract somewhat and then cook[boil?] it for half an hour
<lb/>or somewhat more. Then a piece of red alum,
<lb/>finely pounded, but one must first, in a dish or pan,
<lb/>smilten[melt?] [it] on its own. But one must understand that this does not
<lb/>appear red but is white, but it is so named. And with
<lb/>the outside also cooked, while the wood has simmered
<lb/>for so long, then you pour the soup of alum in the
<lb/>first pot and stir it around with a stocktien. Then the
<lb/>whole thing becomes red. And let it simmer together somewhat, then pour some
<lb/>soup in a little pot. And once it is cool, take white paper and lay it on
</ab>

<pb facs="#f139"/>
<ab>
<lb/>a table [and] begin to paint. But one must lay a bad [cloth]
<lb/>or something that cannot be injured underneath, and hang every
<lb/>sheet from a little cord all over. But then let a 
<lb/>pack of little cords dry and continue thus
<lb/>until that is red enough, according to your taste, all over
<lb/>up to six or seven times. [If] you want to have it
<lb/>shiny, go over it with egg white, finely
<lb/>beaten. This soup is also good to make silk red,
<lb/>especially a white ground or yellow. But [it] must first be
<lb/>washed clean af linten[?bits of the brazilwood?]. But one must cook
<lb/>herein a little bit. It is also good for making withe wood red.
<lb/>And once it is red enough, paint it with [egg] wash. It shines
<lb/>and is like mahogany. The ground of this can serve more
<lb/>than once. With other water and a bit more wood
<lb/>therein and alum, [it] is a good sap again.
<lb/>But the size of the alum [needed for] such a double
<lb/>bucket one surely learns oneself.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f140"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To subtract red [from] cloth
<lb/>One must make lye. Take cold
<lb/>vines and burn it to ashes. Take two pots
<lb/>of rain water and put the ashes and pour the
<lb/>clear lye off into a new earthenware pot
<lb/>and take the red cloth and put it in the lye
<lb/>until it is saturated [lit. overjuiced], and put the pot, well covered
<lb/>with an earthenware lid in the evening from the fire
<lb/>in the lukewarm oven and let it process until
<lb/>the next day at the fire. Then take
<lb/>the same pot and place it on a cupboard
<lb/>with fire (?? chafing dish?) and let it cook for an hour. And let it
<lb/>turn about constantly with a new pot
<lb/>spoon [so] that it doesn't burn. Then take
<lb/>after a new earthenware pot and take the first
<lb/>from the fire and begin to squeeze the cloth out
<lb/>into the second pot, and once the wetness is out, take
<lb/>a half pint of white wine vinegar and stir this in
<lb/>slowly throughout and let it cook on a still
<lb/>fire and stir it so that it does not burn until a ____.
<lb/>And then let it sit until it has sunk, and
<lb/>pour the the uppermost [liquid] off and take the cloth and throw
<lb/>it on the floor and let [it] dry thus.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f141"/>
<ab>
<lb/>And the brightest is for dyeing paper
</ab>

<pb facs="#f142"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Way to dye paper red
<lb/>Put an ounce of potash in
<lb/>an earthenware pot, then boil
<lb/>a stoop of rainwater and
<lb/>pour it, all boiling, on the
<lb/>potash, let it stand
<lb/>untouched until the next day. Then
<lb/>gently, without stirring, pour the clear
<lb/>lye out into another 
<lb/>clean pot. Then take a kanne
<lb/>of this lye, set it to boil
<lb/>and take a pound of red cloth
<lb/>put this in a clean pot and once
<lb/>the lye has boiled, pour it on the
<lb/>cloth, let it somewhat trecken
<lb/>on the fire, turning the cloth
<lb/>from time to time. Once it is all well
<lb/>drunken through, take remove it [from the fire]
<lb/>and let it stand to cool some
<lb/>then put the other kanne of lye
<lb/>on the fire. Let it boil. Then squeeze out
<lb/>the cloth as tightly as you
<lb/>can, and while the lye boils, put
<lb/>the cloth in it. Turn 
<lb/>and stir it well. Let [it] boil for a quarter
<lb/>of an hour. Then let it cool
<lb/>a bit. Squeeze it out again.
<lb/>Then, add all the soup and
<lb/>place this on the fire. Put
<lb/>a susijn of white alum in it.
<lb/>Let this boil a bit. The foam
<lb/>must not be thrown
<lb/>away since good dye can
<lb/>come from it. Then put a bit of
<lb/>white tartar in a pot
<lb/>and pour the boiling dye on top of it.
<lb/>If you see that there is still foam
<lb/>forming, take it off, and and
<lb/>do not put it with the other foam. Then
<lb/>let it sit for two or three days
<lb/>without stirring. Then gently pour
<lb/>all the dye off, and see if the
<lb/>sediment is dirty or if there are black
<lb/>bits in it. If there are any in it, then
<lb/>it isn’t good. If the sediment is clean,
<lb/>put it in with the dye. Then place
<lb/>it again on the fire. If it is
<lb/>purple, it is that there is not enough
<lb/>tartar in it. Also, if there is
<lb/>too much tartar in it, it is
<lb/>too pale. Then put some starch
<lb/>dust-bloom?? in a pot, crush
</ab>

<pb facs="#f143"/>
<ab>
<lb/>it with the cold soup that
<lb/>came from the scum, and once the
<lb/>dye boils, then put it in the pot
<lb/>where the bloom is, boiling it all
<lb/>so that the bloom does not clump.
<lb/>Once the dye becomes purple, then
<lb/>put some more tartar with the bloom
<lb/>until you see that it is a beautiful
<lb/>color. Note that the dye
<lb/>cannot be bottled and cannot
<lb/>be kept for long, but
<lb/>can be reboiled if it has
<lb/>become purple. Let it boil
<lb/>a bit. Then put some tartar in
<lb/>another pot, pour the dye over
<lb/>it, take the foam off, and if
<lb/>it is still too purple, put some
<lb/>more tartar with it until that you see
<lb/>that it is beautiful. And once no more
<lb/>foam appears, one must
<lb/>let it stand until it settles.
<lb/>Then pour it gently out.
<lb/>See if the sediment is good,
<lb/>as [you did] before, and put it in a pot.
<lb/>Let it come to a boil.
<lb/>Take some bloom, as was said
<lb/>before. The dryer the place 
<lb/>where the dye is kept, the
<lb/>better it will keep.
<lb/>One can also paint with this.
<lb/>And if one wants to have
<lb/>light yellow, one must put some
<lb/>rainwater with it.
<lb/>~~~~~~~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f146"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To dye a red color one needs to take a large handful
<lb/>of fine linen and then one takes a half pound of safflower, where those
<lb/>safflowers need to be bundled in a little linen bag and then one puts
<lb/>the safflower that are in the little bag in rainwater for six or seven hours
<lb/>to soak, and now and then turn the little bag in the water.
<lb/>And when it has soaked long enough one needs to wash the little bag,
<lb/>without it coming open, as long as the little bag is still red [OR: long enough until the little bag becomes red]
<lb/>Now, to make the lye, you must take grapevine wood
<lb/>and burn it to ashes, of which ashes one needs to take
<lb/>a pot full and one puts them in a kettle with two pots
<lb/>of rainwater. And leave it thus only a half hour to cook, and then take
<lb/>the kettle off the fire and let it settle, as the lye must
<lb/>be clear. And then begin to dye, end then place the little bag
<lb/>with the safflower in a dish and shake over it a clean
<lb/>little beer glass half full of lye, shake it over the little bag and 
<lb/>wash the little bag with it and then wring the little bag
<lb/>half out, and then add in the whitest linen and once it is wet
<lb/>then squeeze it out, then take a little dish of vinegar and put that little piece
<lb/>of linen in the vinegar, about a little glassfull, then squeeze it out, take again the
<lb/>same little piece of linen that had been in the dye, put it again
<lb/>in the same dye, squeeze it out thus, and put it again in the
<lb/>same vinegar, then squeeze it out. Then, throw the vinegar out and put
<lb/>clean vinegar in the little dish, and then throw the dye out also
<lb/>Wring the aforesaid little bag out, then take the previous
<lb/>piece that is still dyed and put it again therein, so then squeeze it
<lb/>out again and place it again in the vinegar, then squeeze it out again. Then
<lb/>the piece is red enough. Then, you must take once more another white piece
<lb/>of linen, and place it in the dye and then again in the vinegar just as
<lb/>before; and once the dye becomes clear, then throw it out and then lay the
<lb/>little bag in the dish, then pour another half little glass of lye over the
<lb/>little bag, and then wring it therewith, wring the little bag half
<lb/>out, and then begin to dye again in the same manner as before.
<lb/>And as you notice that there is no more dye coming out and [it runs] clear,
<lb/>then you must stop dyeing, then you must wash the red linen, 
<lb/>with some Spanish [i.e., castille] soap, but you must put the soap in a clean
<lb/>little cloth and then beat the little cloth with the soap there in the water. Thus
<lb/>must you then wash [it], piece by piece, in a bucket, and then rinse with clean
<lb/>water. Then wring it out and lay it in a dish and then put 
<lb/>vinegar over it. Let it stand thus therein for a whole night. Then the next day,
<lb/>wring it out, and then lay it to dry on a serge, and that
<lb/>in the dark, and then once it is dry, you must stiffen it with white starch.
<lb/>You must take a quarter of a pound and then let it become cold.
<lb/>Then must you thus stiffen linen, and out of one another, put [it] also on a
<lb/>serge, and that in the dark. Let it dry thus.
<lb/>Now, to make white roses, so must you take white linen and put
<lb/>it in the soap water that the red linen was washed in,
<lb/>and with clear water rinsed, but put it in no vinegar, though
<lb/>stiffen it as before.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f148"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To dye a red color on white 
<lb/>horn, up to a quarter
<lb/>of horn:
<lb/>We take, for 9 large
<lb/>cochenille insects with a half ounce of red red alum
<lb/>put 3 pints of fountain water.
<lb/>One must seethe these together until
<lb/>the soup becomes red. Once done,
<lb/>one must put the quarter of horn
<lb/>in there, in good order, and one
<lb/>lets it seethe until it is a beautiful
<lb/>pink color. Once done, one must
<lb/>take them out of the soup and let [them]
<lb/>dry without rinsing [them], and on
<lb/>top of one another until [they] are somewhat dry
<lb/>—----------------------------------------------------------
<lb/>and once done, open [them].
<lb/>The way to dye white
<lb/>horn, to make it a pink color,
<lb/>that you see the pattern here, this is sold
<lb/>one buys this from the merchant
<lb/>and from the hair dresser, the and [from] other
<lb/>people who make flowers
<lb/>in the world.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f149"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To Bruges
<lb/>Postage with receipt is 
<lb/>eight stuivers and a half
</ab>

<pb facs="#f150"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Red alum, [illeg.], cochenille tartar, all well pounded,
<lb/>to dye the color pink on white horn that you see here,
<lb/>that is ordinarily sold by the merchant. ~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f152"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To make yellow dye
<lb/>Take forth a shilling of
<lb/>gamboge and [take] forth a
<lb/>stuiver of yellow saffron and
<lb/>a stuiver of alum and that
<lb/>together, well broken up,
<lb/>in water
<lb/>Way to paint red
<lb/>Take a quarter
<lb/>brazilwood, a pint vinegar
<lb/>and a half quarter alum
<lb/>and let that seethe until [it reduces to]
<lb/>the half, and then pour the soup out
<lb/>in a flessche[glass/flask?]. That
<lb/>keeps well for three years, and once
<lb/>one wants to use it,
<lb/>thus pour some of that soup in
<lb/>an oyster shell and levigate
<lb/>that 3 to 4 times [until] it [is] clear,
</ab>

<pb facs="#f153"/>
<ab>
<lb/>and then let that stand a day
<lb/>to 2 in the sun or on
<lb/>a low fire ketel that
<lb/>is only a bit thick.
<lb/>And then is it good
<lb/>to use.
<lb/>One prepares also purple
<lb/>dye in the same way,
<lb/>but in place of
<lb/>brazilwood one takes
<lb/>logwood.
<lb/>To make green 
<lb/>dye Take a
<lb/>Take cauliflower leaves
<lb/>without the ribs and
<lb/>pound them, and press that
<lb/>juice out through a rag, and
<lb/>until [you have] a pot of that soup.
<lb/>Take a quarter of verdigris
<lb/>and that all broken up
<lb/>together
<lb/>and let it stand one day 
<lb/>in the sun. And then with
<lb/>a sponge, stroke over
<lb/>the paper 3 to 4 times
</ab>

<pb facs="#f154"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Note: if one wants to have
<lb/>a beautiful violet, one must put in the
<lb/>oyster shell with the dye some
<lb/>unslaked lime ~
<lb/>Note: and put in the red oyster
<lb/>shell with the in the dye some
<lb/>lemon juice. That makes
<lb/>beautiful bright yellow.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f155"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Laundry soap/wax(??) best old beer, the oldest, and the
<lb/>to make, take a ___ wood good
<lb/>__ stuiver brazil wood, and for xxxx
<lb/>off more up to the half, and then
<lb/>and as one wants to use that, so
<lb/>oyster shell, and spill that 2 or 3
<lb/>night xx becomes thick, xx then is
<lb/>rren on paper, as also on
<lb/>ck purple dye but in the
<lb/>mt one logwood ~
</ab>

<pb facs="#f156"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To dye paper yellow
<lb/>One takes a sisein [=coinage type] of saffron, which one lets extract in the quantity
<lb/>of a pint of water. Once it is reasonably well extracted, one pours it off
<lb/>and puts some more water over the saffron to further extract it. One
<lb/>must also have an ounce of gum, which must be soaked for a few days 
<lb/>ahead of time and poured into the extracted saffron once it is cold.
<lb/>[THU: note the “once it is cold” at the end, which is the only clue that the extraction of the saffron takes place with heat]
</ab>

<pb facs="#f158"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To make green paper
<lb/>Take the greens of celery, the youngest of all the ribs,
<lb/>removed and pounded in a mortar, then
<lb/>wrung out, and then pounded again, three times.
<lb/>Then take verdigris and boil it in the soup
<lb/>until it is melted. Put in as much as
<lb/>you want to have green. The more green, the
<lb/>higher [=more intense] the color. Also, a bit of tartar. From time
<lb/>to time, stir until the whole thing is melted. Then take
<lb/>the paper and lay it on a table or board. Then take
<lb/>a little painter’s knife and stroke it thereover.
<lb/>Then the one side being done, leave it to dry,
<lb/>and being well dry, then do the other side, and
<lb/>that so many times until it is green enough.
<lb/>After that, according to taste, take then egg white,
<lb/>stroke it thereover to give a glare once
<lb/>it is very dry.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f160"/>
<ab>
<lb/>To make green dye
<lb/>For a half pound of verdigris,
<lb/>take two cans of rain
<lb/>water and add a half a
<lb/>quarter of tartar, and
<lb/>a pan spoon [pennelepel = large copper spoon used in baking] of pounded alum.
<lb/>Preserve it for one night
<lb/>in a copper bucket or pan. It must
<lb/>be foamy, [geschumt = geschuimt] and
<lb/>must boil down by half.
<lb/>take the green juice
<lb/>in it as long as it is blood-warm.
<lb/>[and is]
<lb/>Verdigris is blue by itself.
<lb/>Take the green juice on the 
<lb/>point of a knife, and should you
<lb/>fear that the verdigris on the side
<lb/>of your pan is not green enough,
<lb/>do not do too much to it,
<lb/>but try it on paper until the
<lb/>color is to your liking,
<lb/>and in case you see that
<lb/>the coloring of your paper is a bit
<lb/>too blue, you must
<lb/>put some more put green color in a dish
<lb/>and add some. [illeg.]
</ab>

<pb facs="#f161"/>
<ab>
<lb/>and when your dye is cooked,
<lb/>put it in a bottle. You can
<lb/>keep it and use as you please,
<lb/> but it is better in the summer
<lb/>than now.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f162"/>
<ab>
<lb/>into which one adds more sap green still.
<lb/>note that the paper you use for this
<lb/>must be fine and [gesloten = dense, perhaps?],
<lb/>and must be coated with
<lb/>warm white starch on one side,
<lb/>and not thick, and the starch should be
<lb/>[made] very even in color with a
<lb/>soft brush. then hang it to dry,
<lb/>and when it is fully dry, lay it down
<lb/>[passen = to fit] so it becomes smooth.
<lb/>then take your green paint, and
<lb/>a part of a sponge
<lb/>to color your paper with,
<lb/>first on the starched side and then
<lb/>[maer naer den eersten en 2 keer = after the first 2 more times].
<lb/>This must be done with a light hand
<lb/>and sparingly so it does not flow, [als = when ]
<lb/>you have gone over your sheet of paper with a light hand,
<lb/>[sijnde = if ] there are still
<lb/>streaks you have missed,
<lb/>they should no longer be there.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f163"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Come, for you must clean it off.
<lb/>You should take the paper
<lb/>but do not hang it
<lb/>to dry, rather lay it
<lb/>on leather or sticks, and it
<lb/>must be fully dry. Before you
<lb/>even go over [wipe] it, the weather must
<lb/>be fair to do this.
<lb/>you must go over the right side 6 times
<lb/>and then the other side 3 to 4 times.
<lb/>~~~
<lb/>I should guess put
<lb/>in a quarter of verdigris
<lb/>for the first time, and
<lb/>it must be pounded. and then
<lb/>further add a can of rain
<lb/>water and a bit more than
<lb/>an ounce of tartar, and a
<lb/>half a spoon of pounded alum
</ab>

<pb facs="#f164"/>
<ab>
<lb/>have rinsed a full pound
<lb/>washed a full pound
<lb/>one our Spanish green
</ab>

<pb facs="#f166"/>
<ab>
<lb/>of our verdigris,
<lb/>a half pound of white wax,
<lb/>and three quarters of other
<lb/>a half pound, and a half
<lb/>quarter a rinschen hast [that you have rinsed?];
<lb/>all of it well melted and stir [it] together without
<lb/>boi boiling. Next [one] needs to plunge the
<lb/>paper inside [with] a bande [i.e. length of fabric] at the same time
<lb/>the width of three taille [regular size?], roughly,
<lb/>but the same length as the the paper is
<lb/>in its length.
<lb/>This is for the confectioner
<lb/>who make desserts, and because
<lb/>you want to make [it] with [it].
<lb/>But if you see that the paper
<lb/>is not as green as you wish,
<lb/>into this you need to put more
<lb/>of the green of Spain, or otherwise said,
<lb/>verdegris.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f167"/>
<ab>
<lb/>This monstrance represents
<lb/>the passion of Jesus
<lb/>Christ, with the triumphal
<lb/>coronation of the very holy
<lb/>sacrament. ~~~
<lb/>This monstrance represents
<lb/>the baptism of Jesus Christ,
<lb/>which our sweet savior ~
<lb/>received from St John the Baptist. ∞
<lb/>The holy spirit, with his reasons,
<lb/>placed upon the head of Jesus
<lb/>Christ, the cross, with the
<lb/>crown of thorns; ~~~
<lb/>This monstrance repre-
</ab>

<pb facs="#f168"/>
<ab>
<lb/>and a quarter of copper-red and let
<lb/>it [be] seen for your uses.
<lb/>for blue
<lb/>Pour three buckets of warm urine 
<lb/>into a vat that is very clean. 
<lb/>Then take ten ounces of indigo and three
<lb/>fourths of a pot of finely pounded [gestoken?]
<lb/>ashes, pull it ["troocken"=troken?] into a new pot, with
<lb/>two pints of rainwater, then pour in
<lb/>six ounces of madder and two handfuls of chalk, 
<lb/>and let it sit for eight or nine days, it does not matter.
<lb/>Then a half pint of brandy and a stuiver of [animal intestine or, more likely, bran?]
<lb/>for black
<lb/>Take fourteen and a half pints of gall nuts, a half
<lb/>pint of madder, and two pounds of sumac [smack]. Let it
<lb/>cook for an hour. Cool it down quickly.
<lb/>Add to the same
<lb/>water a half pound of Proveçal wood
<lb/>with three pounds of copperas and let it cook
<lb/>another half hour.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f170"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Way to make ashes from grapevine tendrils
<lb/>One can these, by a pure heart, without mixing
<lb/>other ashes in, that are newly burnt, one puts it on the fire and the ashes
<lb/>all together in a bad/old earthenware pot, which one from time
<lb/>to time pokes, until it is all consumed.
<lb/>To make lye from grapevine-tendril ash
<lb/>Take three handfuls of ashes [scooped] with two hands, and 7 or 8
<lb/>pints of rain or fountain water, let this cook until [it reduces to] 4 or 5
<lb/>pints, should be cooked in a clean [metal] marmite. Once it is
<lb/>removed from the fire, it must be cast [i.e., levigated] into a metal pot that
<lb/>has not been used for any other thing, such as dyeing red,
<lb/>leaving the ashes, so much as possible, on the bottom of the
<lb/>marmite. The next day, one pours the ashes through a cloth
<lb/>into another pot, still careful not to move [what is on]
<lb/>the bottom. The lye is then good to use to dye a pink color,
<lb/>as follows here.
<lb/>Take a quarter or half pound of safflower, put it in a little
<lb/>white linen bag, securely tied, place it to soak
<lb/>in rain or fountain water. One washes(?) the safflower a little
<lb/>itself, changing the water two times, and then letting [it] soak
<lb/>from five-thirty in the evening until five-thirty in the morning.
<lb/>And then is it washed, and from time to time, its
<lb/>water is changed until it is clear. The bag should not
<lb/>be wrung out but removed from the water with the hands, except for
<lb/>the last time: then, the little bag must be very firmly wrung out,
<lb/>as much as is possible.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f171"/>
<ab>
<lb/>After, one pulls the safflower out of the bag and puts it
<lb/>in a large, flat[-bottomed] pot, and once everything is thoroughly picked
<lb/>[out of the bag], one sprinkles there a little rain or fountain water
<lb/>over [it]. Then one pours into the safflower a pint of lye made
<lb/>from the ashes of grapevine tendrils. Then is the pot covered
<lb/>with another of the same size, so that it
<lb/>can catch the air. Set it in a dark place,
<lb/>set a covering-cloth over it, and let it proceed
<lb/>for 2 hours, and [it] must then be bruised for 15 minutes.
<lb/>One must remove it by handfuls. Once one can
<lb/>take no more [out], pour the rest into the bag again, [and] this
<lb/>is wrung out into a clean pot. One prepares immediately
<lb/>another pot with some white wine vinegar, in which the fabric
<lb/>is made wet. Being well drunk, one takes these [i.e., the vinegar-soaked fabric and the lyed petals]
<lb/>all together, gives them into the hands of the person that
<lb/>bruised and and wrung out the safflower, which entire mass alike had
<lb/>been set in the dye. Wash these same [things] well one by one.
<lb/>Proceed with a light hand as quickly as is possible.
<lb/>The fabric, having her color, is washed again, piece by
<lb/>piece, after having removed [un-dunked] it well. Put them in verjuice
<lb/>after [they] are squeezed out as before. [They] are rinsed in three or 4
<lb/>pots following before prepared with 2 or 3 pints of clean
<lb/>rain or fountain water, where after one washes a few pieces of fabric
<lb/>therein [once] the first color is rinsed in, which serves
<lb/>as a pale color and is then dried together in the attic. [is there a little flower at the end?]
</ab>

  </div></body>
      </text>